<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Bushell's abridgment of the Lord Chancellor Bacon's philosophical theory in mineral prosecutions ...</title>
            <author>Bushell, Thomas, 1594-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B17399</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11658152</idno>
  <idno type="VID">199121</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248500243</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B304</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11658152</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B17399)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199121)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 10:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Bushell's abridgment of the Lord Chancellor Bacon's philosophical theory in mineral prosecutions ...</title>
                  <author>Bushell, Thomas, 1594-1674.</author>
                  <author>Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626. New Atlantis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 14, 8, 12, 4, 4, 8, 12, 9-16 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Mines and mineral resources --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199121:1"/>
            <p>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Bushell's ABRIDGMENT Of the Lord Chancellor BACON'S PHILOSOPHICAL THEORY IN Mineral Prosecutions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Impressa of Mr.</hi> Bushell's <hi>Golden Medal, of which see immediately before that LORD'S</hi> Atlantis.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>·FRA· BACON· VICECO· S<seg rend="sup">CT.</seg> ALBAN· ANGLIAE· CANCELL·</p>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <p>EST· QVI· CLAVSA· RECLVDIT· THO· BVSHELL· DEVS·</p>
            </figure>
            <p>London <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 1650</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:199121:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199121:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable <hi>WILLIAM LENTHAL</hi> Speaker to the PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY old Master the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor <hi>Bacon</hi> would often say, That the magnificence of a Parliament, consisted much in the presence of their Prince; and that the reflection of his Royal Affection, was as a foil to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them as Diamonds of greater value in their Countries service. If those natural flaws of Self-interest, were not frequently known to become a motive to make them forfeit their Trust and subvert their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which invited that Lords obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to reflect upon such a Model of new Laws, as no forc'd power should be able to take away the regallity of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Rights, nor their prerogative have
<pb facs="tcp:199121:3"/> a Medium to intrench upon the priviledge of their Subjects; and that his Phyloso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy should be the sole revenue to support the Magie of so magnificent a Machini, without any other imposition on the people, then its attendance upon Providence; and to change the temper of loose and avariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous minds into Moral and divine virtues: but that Lord being commanded by King <hi>James,</hi> to write the life of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, and his great imployments in State affairs, were the divertisements which retarded his inclination to that study, and left only the essay of his Mineral Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy to support his <hi>Solomons House,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed in his <hi>New Atlantis,</hi> as a test whereby the success of his other experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments might be judged. And now most Honored Sir, you having received the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> his Letter to the Parliament, in answer of mine, touching the making good my Articles, as also to recompence my great sufferings, hath made me so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume
<pb facs="tcp:199121:3"/> on your Lordship, as to beseech you to patronize this publication of my proceedings, and the rather for that I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by the weekly accurrance. Your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor hath sent a Letter of Thanks to the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> in the Name of the whole House, for his late opportune service done to the Honorable Parliament, which hath emboldned me the more to put your Honor in mind of a result of the said Lords Letter directed to your self, &amp; dated the 29 of <hi>July</hi> last, least the interpretation of your Honors Letter should be held in the Diary of a Complement, when the L. <hi>Fairfax</hi> his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is laid aside, which concerns his and the Parliaments Honor to make good, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause his Lordship did me the favor to send me a true Copy of what was writ, I have made bold humbly to present you with the grounds and reasons at large, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd him to it, that the Parliaments wisdom might take a more present care of the whole matter, rather then the glory of such a
<pb facs="tcp:199121:4"/> work should perish for want of a right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding. And if it may seem to any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of that Honorable House, too great a favor for me to have my Articles made good, I shall humbly pray no more, then that their Justice may protect my Mineral adventures at <hi>Rowpits</hi> upon the Forrest of <hi>Mendip,</hi> and other deserted places, and to defend my Feoffees in trust, who have resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to make a true trial of my Lords Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy in that affair, since most Men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted me not well in my wits, for attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the seeming impossibility of recovering their drowned conditions, otherwise those publick spirits will doubtless inevitably suffer. From whence God lead your Lordship by the hand, and all others that will take the pains to read the ensuing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, for then my Genius invites me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, I shall have their unanimous consent so an errevocable Act like the <hi>Meeds</hi> and <hi>Persians,</hi> which is and shall be the Prayer</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your most humble servant</hi> Tho. Bushell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:199121:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF thou hast not faith to believe that Philosophy is the Mistress of all Humane Learning, and comes nearest to the Idea of Divine Knowledge, thou canst not hope for any good success in the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon's</hi> Mineral Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, nor from the Practical experience of me his Pupil: since thou mayest learn from the oraculous truth of Holy Writ, That sacred Providence never conferr'd intended blessings on the incredulous, or such as preferr'd the fruits of any Designe above the Creators glory. For that Lord was of opinion, that little Philosophy brings a man to Atheism; but the intrinsecal know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof teacheth him Religion, and to magnifie the Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for the admirable Varieties of his handmaid Nature. For he which denieth there is a God, destroys his own original and nobility; for a man is of kin to the beast by his body, and if he be not kin to God by his spirit, he is a base and ignoble creature. If then the ensuing Remonstrance of my Mineral proficiencie, and intended designs thereupon, shall be rightly weighed, and maturely scanned by thy Intellectuals without partiality, I have my desired ends; intending thee opportunity (by the experience of my known pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice) to advance thy name with honor and profit, in the honest profession of a Miner; and if that prove idoneous to the eye of thy speculation, let me then obtain thy approbation, and utmost abilities to further the progress of this work so happily begun, and thereby make thy self as a corner-stone in this Philosophical fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick. For thou maist know (gentle Reader) that my humble Petition to the Parliament prays no more then the concession and confirmation to me of all drowned and deserted Mineral works, whereon to try, if that Lord's Philosophical Theory can give life to their dead condition; hoping thereby (if happily accomplished)
<pb facs="tcp:199121:5"/> to make his merit appear the more remarkable in the Structure of his <hi>Solomon's House,</hi> modell'd out in his <hi>New Atlantis;</hi> and this Nation to know the glory of her concealed Riches, by that Example.</p>
            <p>But to encourage thy Genius in so commendable an enterprise for the honor of thy Country, I must give thee to understand, that this was the renowned Parliament which gave the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> and the Lord <hi>Say</hi> power to capitulate with me concerning <hi>Lundy,</hi> and grant me Articles of War on their behalf, as by their Letters in answer of mine doth appear; together with the humble and earnest Petition of the Western Gentlemen vers'd in Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, to the then Ruling power, for the speedy ratification thereof, without my personal attendance, lest the inevitable invasion of age should prevent my service therein: And therefore I doubt not but the same Providence which hath brought them together in the strange vicissitudes of these later times, will dictate to their wisdoms, that this my Mineral service (dedicated by my obliged gratitude to my Lord <hi>Bacon's</hi> Philosophical Design) was origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally transmitted to their prudential care, as well as the rest of publique affairs; if their understandings be not clouded, as were the judgments of those Senators concerning <hi>Columbus</hi> his propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>7.</hi> to our perpetual repentance: For that Lord my Master would often say, That if our three Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons could produce but such a number of pious and publique-minded true Philosophers, as <hi>Abraham</hi> proposed of Righteous ones to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse <hi>Sodom,</hi> who would freely bequeath the mysteries and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions of their beneficent Arts to their Countries good, he did verily believe his Mineral Design (if by them undertaken) would in process of time, by a noble and innocent profit, exceed the magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent advantages of the <hi>China</hi>-Trade, or the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can Revenue, through new discoveries of our Native Minerals, and philosophical cures of their natural crudities. For whereas the <hi>Spaniard</hi> (to the destruction of innocent people) hath consumed many millions of his Western vassals with excessive labor in gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Gold and Silver (though found in a perfect species) and by making use of that volatile body of poisonous Quicksilver to
<pb facs="tcp:199121:5"/> reduce its Atoms into pure Ingots of either quality; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for many years past hath been forc'd to buy the persons of multitudes of <hi>Moors</hi> at <hi>Guiny</hi> and <hi>Cape Blanco</hi> for the same imployment: Here on the contrary, by that Lords philosophical new way of Mining, and Separation, we shall minister the bread of comfort to innumerable families, and adde to our Common-wealth millions of native Silver, which our dull Ancestors sent away and lost in the crude body of our Lead; by which ignorance (only since the Conquest) our detriment amounts unto Three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty Millions of pounds Sterling, as by a just calculation of the Transported plainly appears: And therefore I shall leave the consequence of both to the judicious Reader, which of those Miners at the day of Judgment will be best esteemed, He which gets most Silver, and yet destroys millions of men in his way of working; or the other which preserves them, and gets the less.</p>
            <p>But because thy candid judgment may not suspect my Overtures as the Chymera of a phanatick brain, or some project of deceit, I will demonstrate unto thee the truth of my proceedings; which in truth is thus: My affection to this work, and obedience to that Lords commands, moved me as his Pupil to practise such Notions of his Mineral Theory, as might conduce to the honor and profit of our Nation; although homebred simplicity were my education, and a younger Brothers fortune my portion to support that enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise without a partner, which his Lordship ever advised me to decline, and trust wholly to Providence: But most perswasively at that time when he discovered to me the dearest Secrets of this his Design; adding, as a conjuration of gratitude, integrity, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry and constancy in the prosecution thereof, this form of speech, if my memory be faithful. [<hi>Now,</hi> Bushell, <hi>I have dealt with you in your naked simplicity, as God did with</hi> Adam <hi>in Paradise, when he gave him so large a royaltie over all in that Garden, with so small an exception as the interdicted Tree: For I have made thee the Secretary of all my Mineral Studies, no ways restraining thee in the practice; only I prohibit thy arrogating to thy self the honor thereof, if it
<pb facs="tcp:199121:6"/> shall prove fortunate; and the imploying such Treasures as shall be gained thereby, any way which shall not conduce to the raising, qualifying and endowing my</hi> Solomon's House, <hi>modell'd in my</hi> New Atlantis, <hi>to my own proposed ends, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the duty of an obliged Servant, and faithful Steward.</hi>] Wherefore thus resolved, <hi>I</hi> contracted with the late King, and the succeeding Lord Protector, for a Grant to search their barren Mountains, and to coin all such Silver as my industry should gain out of them (Providence assisting) if I should cut through their lowest levels to discover the Meander of such Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral riches as are conceived by that Lord to lie in their Bases; six of which are called, the <hi>Darr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, Broome-lloyd, Cumsum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock, Tallabont, Commervin</hi> and <hi>Cummustwith:</hi> And my success in following his Rules were crowned with such unexpected blessings, that I did confidently believe, all Mountains in whose superficies I found such Mineral Rakes and Sparrs contained veins of like species and value as those I had pierced, and the fittest Flowers (being native Gemms) to adorn a Prince's Diadem, if happily cut; for so they might produce most honorable improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the Royal Revenue: A means more pious and heroick to happifie any Soveraign Prince, then by heavy Taxes, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoms and Impositions, to draw their Subjects treasure into their own coffers, especially when they exact the fruit of poor mens labors to consume in their prodigious expences; which may justly be feared hath been the accursed thing that hath so much displeased the sacred eye of the All-disposer, and occasioned such tragical al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations in some of their successions: By the latest of which my Mineral procedures have been interrupted, and I have suffered unspeakable losses through the hostile effects of the late Wars, whereby my hopeful Embrions became abortive; until I attempted the recovering those deserted Works mentioned in my annexed Remonstrance; to make an exact trial of my Masters philosophical way in discovering the unknown riches of this Nation, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem my lost Credit, through the aid of the Divine providence, which I have humbly implored in my Prayer conjunct to the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Discourse; hoping by such harmless Adventures to revive
<pb facs="tcp:199121:6"/> the memory of Noble <hi>Bacon,</hi> and to procure the confirmation of my Agreement with the Miners by a Parliament-stamp, as it was ratified by the late Protector, upon the then Lord Chief Justice <hi>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>-John's</hi> approbation of the honor of that work: For who can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, that in such a multitude as they are, all can be morally ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, when Christ himself amongst his twelve Disc ples had one a Traitor?</p>
            <p>But now seriously considering that the taper of my life burns in the socket, (I having already numbred twelve lustres of years) I intend to begin the foundation of that Philosophical fabrick (modell'd out in my Lords <hi>Atlantis</hi>) by placing a select Society of such aforesaid Philosophers in the City of <hi>Wells,</hi> whose vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Studies may first intend only the discovery of such Mineral Treasures, as are conceived by some learned Miners to be guarded by the subterranean Spirits lest my approaching period should pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the experiment, and frustrate the many grateful intentions which my soul thirsteth to compleat. And if Providence crowns these my endevors in the <hi>West,</hi> all other deserted Works in the <hi>North</hi> may be recovered by the like practice. So that if by that Lords directions I should now at the last bring the deserted Works of a contemptible Soil (without damage to any person) to free me from obloquie, by clearing <hi>40000 <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> Debt contracted for the late King, and my self, (which I have been utterly disabled to satisfie, ever since by the sad effects of the late Civil wars all my own Estate hath been detained from me) which is very probable; should I not be barbarously ingrateful, if I did not attribute such a blessing to the Almighties providence? and conclude, that any person whatsoever who should seek to obstruct so hopeful a work for his Countries general good, was accursed in his conception, and ought to be abhorr'd as a plague-sore.</p>
            <p>Gentle Reader, I write not this to constrain thy faith to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility of my Lord <hi>Bacon's</hi> Judgment in Philosophy, but only beg thy Talion-justice in thy censure hereof; and let not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valencie of malice (which trepann'd me into this Restraint) throw a prejudice upon the Design, or the the Modeller thereof: For (be confident) my nature scorns revenge, if in my power: God's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
<pb facs="tcp:199121:7"/> is over, and in all our actions and sufferings; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, like <hi>Joseph</hi> sold into <hi>Egypt,</hi> my restraint here may beget a deliverance of all penitent Convicts, who (to expiate their crimes) had rather serve seven years in so hopeful a work within their native Country, then undergo a slavish condition in a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Plantation: For that Lord (in order to this) would usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally say, <hi>Nothing like a Diamond to cut a Diamond for hardness;</hi> and, <hi>The dead in Law were fittest to recover the dead in Opinion.</hi> Upon which gracious favor, I shall most wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly remain a Prisoner my self, without seeking the fruition of my Articles, until I have perfected the same, by the Searcher of all hearts, and in the wisdom of this Honorable State. But if their Clemencie shall be so graciously propitious to this Design of that Lords <hi>Atlantis,</hi> as to grant me my Estate upon the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> his Letter of request, and his justification of my right therein, I shall most willingly submit the whole profit thereof to be consigned to Trustees deputed by themselves, and perswade the major part of my honest Creditors to attend the issue of satisfaction from the Mineral Discoveries of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your most humble Servant,</hi> Tho. Bushell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:199121:7"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS of the ensuing TREATISE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>MAster <hi>Bushels</hi> Letter to the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> containing his suffering condition, and imploring his Honors redress according to Articles.</item>
               <item>The late Kings Letter to Mr. <hi>Bushel,</hi> concerning the surrender of the Isle of <hi>Lundy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Bushell's</hi> Articles upon his surrender of the said Isle.</item>
               <item>His late Highness confirmation of the said Articles.</item>
               <item>The Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> his Letter to the <hi>Speaker,</hi> in Answer of Mr. <hi>Bushells,</hi> wherein he justifieth his Articles, and desireth that the Parliament would recompence him for his great sufferings by their timely assistance.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Bushells</hi> Declaration, assuring all persons to ease the Taxes of such Parishes, wherein Minerals shall be discovered by their Plough, and notice thereof given to him by them, as also his former proceedings thereupon.</item>
               <item>The confirmation of his Agreement with the Miners of <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyp,</hi> encouraging him to go on in so desperate a design, by the late Protector <hi>Richard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Remonstrance to the present Parliament.</item>
               <item>The Case of a Mine-Royal judged to be by the most learned Lawyers under their hands.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Bushells</hi> Minerall Overtures to the Councill.</item>
               <item>A Letter to Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi> relating some strange accidents which hapned in the Mines.</item>
               <item>The Petition of the Proprietors, Commoners and Mineral Bounders of the deserted and drowned Mines within the Counties
<pb facs="tcp:199121:8"/> of <hi>Cornwal</hi> and <hi>Devon,</hi> for the speedy making good of Mr. <hi>Bushells</hi> Articles without his personal attendance.</item>
               <item>A Letter to Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi> from the Lords Proprietors of <hi>Hing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston Down,</hi> encouraging him to go on with that work, according to his Draught, and <hi>Merlins</hi> prophecie therein.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Bushells</hi> Draught of <hi>Hingston Down,</hi> modell'd on by the late Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Bushells</hi> Letter to the Miners of <hi>Mendyp,</hi> with their Answer, and their Juries Order thereupon.</item>
               <item>The humble Petition of the Mineral-Bounders within the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Somerset,</hi> for the Confirmation of Mr. <hi>Bushells</hi> Articles without his personal attendance.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Basbee's</hi> Affidavit.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Christophers Whright's</hi> Affidauit touching Mr. <hi>Bushells</hi> desperate Anventures in <hi>Rowpits</hi> in the Forrest of <hi>Mendyp.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Testimony of some Miners of <hi>Mendyp</hi> to the Council concerning the same.</item>
               <item>Another Order of the grand Jury of <hi>Chewton</hi> in confirmation of the former, and for redressing any injuries that shall (for the future) be offered to Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi> in his workes.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Bushells</hi> Petition to the late King to have Condemned men (for Petty-felonies) to work in the Mines.</item>
               <item>The Speech of the late Bishop of <hi>Worcester</hi> (neer his death) to Mr. <hi>Bushell,</hi> concerning two rich Mines by him discovered.</item>
               <item>A Letter of humble Thanks to the late King from the Judges and Justices of <hi>Wales,</hi> in behalf of all the Inhabitants of that Principality, for the Granu of his Mint to Mr. <hi>Bushell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Cirtificate from the Miners, Smelters, &amp;c. to the Lords of his Majesties honorable Privy Council, concerning new Discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Mines made by Mr. <hi>Bushell.</hi> A Cirtificate from the Assay-masters of the Mint, &amp;c. to the Council.</item>
               <item>An Order of the Lords in Parliament for Mr. <hi>Bushells</hi> security and encouragement in the Mines in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ardiganshire.</hi> The Lord Keepers Letter to the Justices of Assise in reference to the said Order.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Bushells</hi> Letter of invitation to condemned-men (for
<pb facs="tcp:199121:8"/> Petty-felonies) rather to work in the Mines of their own Country, then be banish'd to slavery in Forein parts</item>
               <item>His Letter to his fellow Prisoners for Debt, in mind or body.</item>
               <item>The late Kings Letter of invitation to Mr. <hi>Bushell,</hi> concerning his procedure in Mineral discoveries.</item>
               <item>The Merchants Letter of <hi>Barnstaple</hi> to Mr. <hi>Bushell,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their accommodation of transporting his Lead and Oar <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>The Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> his Letter to the Speaker of Parliament touching Mr. <hi>Bushells</hi> reality of his surrendring <hi>Lundy</hi>-Isle, and his humble request to make good his Articles.</item>
               <item>The Miners Contemplative Prayer in his solitary Delves:</item>
               <item>The Impressa of Mr. <hi>Bushells</hi> Golden Medal to be given in mart (by his Friends) for performance of his undertakings, and the Draught of a Bill to that purpose.</item>
               <item>The Lord <hi>S. Albans Atlantis</hi> (usually annexed to his <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral History</hi>) is likewise conceiv'd (by Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi>) a fit Subject for the Reader to peruse, as an Appendix to this Mineral Treatise.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:199121:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199121:9"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>BƲSHEL'S</hi> LETTER To the Right Honorable the L<seg rend="sup">ORD</seg> FAIRFAX Touching his Articles of VVar.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the inclosed Remonstrance you will discern the readiness of my industry to do my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey service, and by my Articles of War, how much your Lordship and my Lord <hi>Say</hi> and <hi>Seal</hi> are ingaged in Honor to see them ratified; and therefore I shall not need to put your Lordship in minde of more then what proceeds from your quick-sighted <hi>genius,</hi> and springs from the veins of your Noble Blood, especially when the fidelity of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance on my part (as a private Gentleman) shall be ballanced and scanned by your own Wisdom. For (my Lord) I held my Articles of War, made by such persons of quality, and from the Authority of Parliament, more impregnable then the strongest Garison: And why I should be made the onely Trophee of Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, by being rendred thus into a Prison upon an Arrest, through my confidence of your ingagements to protect me, when (by my Publick Actions) the Honor of a Parliament, and your own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests are bound to make them good, I know not, neither do I see the Equity or Justice of it: For it is impossible your Lordships
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199121:10"/> should conceive my judgment so weak (I having the late Kings Monitory Letter, a true Copy whereof is here under written) when you shall consider the great Debts I have contracted for him and my self, as to part from so Tenable a place as <hi>Lundy,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my Estate restored to enable me to pay them, or my person pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected till I got the possession, but much rather have died in the place, then be exposed to a loathsome Prison, by the common rigor of Bailiffs and Sergeants; unless it be decreed by the Eternal Power, that future Ages shall finde on Record, there was a time when a Writ, procured by a mechanick fellow, did baffle an Ordinance of Parliament, impowering their General and one of the greatest Peers of the Realm to Treat with me concerning that Garison. In a word, my Lord, solid judgments do conceive, that my person cannot suffer more by imprisonment, then your Honors in the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of all States for suffering it. I write not this my Lord to free my self from prison, until I pay the utmost farthing of any just debt I ow, either for the late King, or upon my own score; if both your ingaged Honors are not concerned in my Restraint, but onely crave liberty to pursue those Mines which Providence hath in all probability designed to pay such patient Creditors, Orphans and Widows, as never laid other action upon me then their daily prayers: For (my Lord) the fears of not enjoying (when brought to perfection) do far transcend any doubts I have of recovering Mineral Riches out of the hardest Rocks;<note place="margin">Isa. 45.3.</note> and since Divine bounty was pleased to confer such hidden Treasures upon a Heathen King, it were a sin of a high nature in me, that profess Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity to suspect a lesser success, when the All-seeing Eye well knows my designed end is no more then the love of gratitude to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue those Philosophical Notions described in the Lord <hi>Bacons New Atlantis,</hi> for magnifying the God of Nature in his secret Works of Nature: And therefore I could wish and humbly pray, That the Nobleness of your Spirit might be the Corner Stone of such a Fabrick to posterity, since his Highness Heroick Disposition hath vouchsafed to protect the same from any powerful oppressor (upon the Lord Chief Justice St. <hi>Johns</hi> and the Lord <hi>Say's</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation) for the general good.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:199121:10"/>
            <p>My Lord, these sufferings in my Reputation, Life, and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune by this imprisonment, I was resolved to submit unto in a silent patience; but some of my distressed friends, fearing the deep wounds in my head from that unhappy Arrest might prove to be mortal, have occasioned this my Address, upon a confident hope, that the Parliaments Wisdom will not deny a favor of such just concernment to your Lordships Merits, and the Lord Viscount <hi>Sayes,</hi> if their more weighty affairs can but permit them leasure to pry into that Politick Act of State whereby Garisons were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired for great sums, and then it is conceived, your Lordships care in securing <hi>Lundy</hi> Isle will redound to your greater Honor, when they shall consider that much Piracy might have been commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that place without control, which was surrendred (through your Prudencies) without any other condition then one person to be protected until the possession of his estate were restored to satisfie the just debts of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships most humble Servant <hi>Thomas Bushel.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>April 18. 1659.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Majesties Answer to Mr. <hi>Bushel,</hi> concerning the Surrender of <hi>Lundy.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>BUSHEL,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE have perused thy Letter, in which We finde thy care to answer the Trust We at first reposed in thee: Now since the place is inconsiderable in it self, and yet may be of great advantage unto you in respect of your Mines. We do hereby give you leave to use your discretion in it, with this Caution, That you take example by Our Selves, and be not over-credulous of vain promises, which hath made Us great onely in Our Sufferings, and will not discharge your Debts.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From Newcastle.</hi>
                  <date>14 <hi>July.</hi> 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199121:11"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Bushels</hi> Articles upon his Surrender of the Isle of <hi>Lundy.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Propositions, Articles, Conditions, Ingagements, and Agreements made, concluded, and assented unto, the Tenth of <hi>September,</hi> in the year 1647. between his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> Knight, Lord General, and the Lord Viscount <hi>Say</hi> and <hi>Seal,</hi> of the one part, and <hi>Thomas Bushel</hi> Esq; Governor of the Island of <hi>Lundy</hi> for the Kings Majesty of the other part, in pursuance of several Orders of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of both Kingdoms, and an Order or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Lords and Commons in Parliament, as followeth,</p>
            </argument>
            <p>FIrst, It is agreed that the said Mr. <hi>Bushel</hi> shall Surrender and Deliver up the said Island unto the said Lord <hi>Say,</hi> or unto such person as he shall appoint, and all Ammunition, and Magazin there.</p>
            <q>And that in consideration thereof, The Delinquency of the said Mr. <hi>Bushel</hi> shall be taken off, and all Sequestration in respect thereof discharged; and he the said Mr <hi>Bushel</hi> shall be restored unto his Estate, and such right as he or his Assigns had in the Mines of <hi>Devon, Cornwal,</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> before these troubles; and all the persons with him in the Island, and not being persons of quality, shall be pardoned of their Delinquency, and suffered to live quietly at home, not acting any thing contrary to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliament.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That Mr. <hi>Bushel</hi> shall be protected from Arrest, until he obtain the possession of his said Estate.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO. FAIRFAX.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:199121:11"/>
            <head>His late Highness confirmation of the said Articles.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>OLIVER P.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHereas <hi>Tho. Bushel</hi> Esq; by his Articles of War, dated the 10th. of <hi>Sept.</hi> 1647. is to be protected from Arrests, until he shal obtain the possession of his estate, and having found that he is so just to all his Creditors, as by his own Petition, he hath tendred his whole estate to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided amongst them by the Commissioners appointed by the late Act for relief of Creditors and poor Prisoners, that he may be the more free to serve this Common-wealth, in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off the taxes from the people by such publike profits as he shall raise out of his Mineral discoveries, in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of his duty to this State, and gratitude to his deceased Master the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon.</hi> We have therefore thought fit, and do hereby promise upon our word, to grant unto him and his Adventurers such conditions, accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, immunities and priviledges in consideration thereof, and for carrying on of that affair expressed at large in his printed Overtures, as under the hands of the Lords Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners for the great Seal, and the Lord chief Justice of either Bench, or any two of them shall be approved of and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to us to be granted, ratified and confirmed, Given under our hand and Seal this second day of <hi>February,</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> Letter to the Speaker of the Parliament.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Master Speaker,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Cannot but be sensible of any thing that reflects on the Honour of the Parliament as on my self, who for their service hath gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Articles to several persons as importancie of affairs required, and particularly to your Petitioner <hi>Mr. Bushel;</hi> but of late there hath bin some obstruction in due execution of them to the prejudice of such as cast themselves on your protection, which <hi>Mr. Bushel</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:199121:12"/> more readily did, in hope of performance of those Articles made upon his surrender of the Isle of <hi>Lundy;</hi> with the Lord <hi>Say</hi> and my self on the behalfe of the Parliament, then conceived most reasonable as his papers herewith doe express; therefore intreat at your first opportunity, you would acquaint the Honorable House with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of my humble desires, which is, That they would make good <hi>Mr. Bushels</hi> Articles, and be pleased to recompence his great suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings with their timely assistance, that he may be better inabled to satisfie his Creditors which he cannot doe but by pursuite of such Mineral discoveries as Art and Experience hath taught him which will not only be their advantage in securing those debts, but render him more capable of doing considerable service to the Commonwealth. And in so just an Act you will preserve the Justice and Honour of the Parliament, and his, who hath ever been,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your most humble Servant <hi>T. Fairfax.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Bath, <date>
                     <hi>29</hi> July, <hi>1659.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>These,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>
                     <hi>To the right Honorable</hi> William Lenthall <hi>Speaker of the Parliament of</hi> England.</salute>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <head>A Declaration of <hi>Thomas Bushel</hi> Esq; Touching Mines Royal, to all persons whatsoever, that are Lovers of the Commonwealth, and Promoters of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Actions, as well for the Welfare of the same, as for their own private Interest in a lawful way, to ease them of their Taxes.</head>
            <p>WHereas his Highness the <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived good assurance of the great Industry and long Experience of the said <hi>Thomas Bushel</hi> in Mineral discoveries, (demonstrated in his late Overtures presented to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of State) hath been graciously pleased, by his Letters Pattents under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> bearing date the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199121:12"/> 16 day of <hi>February</hi> 1654 to grant to the said <hi>Thomas Bushel,</hi> and his Coadventurers, full power and Authority to Dig, Delve, and search for all Mines Royal within the Territories of this Commonwealth, (rendring to the State every fifth Tun of all such Oar as shall hold Gold or Silver worth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining:) Provided, that if in pursuit thereof, (by carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on their chargeable Adits or Delves thorow the lowest Levels of Hills or Mountains) they discover any Mines that do not prove Royal, they shall then pay every tenth Tun of such Oar, as they shall there dig or delve, to the Proprietors of such Lands, and not to the State; that so the expectation of all moderate persons may be answered with a certain Profit without Charge, and himself and his Co-Adventurers not discouraged in a work of so publike concernment. In refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence whereunto, his Highness the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> hath also graciously ratified to the said <hi>Thomas Bushel</hi> the former power he had to Coyn all such silver as he shall refine out of the Oar of the abovesaid Mines Royal: and in humble resentment of which favor, and as a grateful motive to stir up all mens affections and industries to the discovery of such Mines, the said <hi>Thomas Bushel</hi> hath engaged himself, to his Highness the <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> and his honourable Councel, and doth hereby engage himself, to free all such Parishes from their Taxes, or give to their poor the value thereof, in which any such Mine or Mines shall by the Parishoners of the same be disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto him, so long as they shall be wrought; if by the judgement of the two next Justices of the Peace, they shall be proved rich and valuable.</p>
            <p>The Premises seriously considered, the said <hi>Thomas Bushel</hi> earnestly entreateth all and every of you his loving Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who are well-affected to the Commonwealth, That you will unanimously be pleased to joyn your utmost Industry and Observation, in the diligent Discovery of all such Shods, Spars, Rakes, and Veins, as may (to your best judgement) appear Mineral, in your digging, delving, or plowing your Grounds: that, as much as in you lies, you may all agree in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199121:13"/> this great Work, and act as the united Faculties of one man; whereby you may not onely prove instrumental to the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying Gods glory in the excellency of his Creation, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate your Memories by the noble Titles of loving Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triots to your native Country: The honest desire whereof, hath so enflamed the said <hi>Thomas Bushel,</hi> that he unfeignedly professeth, as in the presence of God, That had he now an estate equal with the richest private person in <hi>England,</hi> he would employ it all in pursuance of so hopeful a Design, for the good of this Commonwealth, and in obedience to the Commands of his honoured Lord and Master, the late Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon;</hi> albeit he hath in his former Undertakings of this nature, met with some of so contrary a disposition, that out of a poor private respect to their Herbage on some barren Mountains, by him proved to the Parliament not worth 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> an Acre <hi>per annum,</hi> they for seven yeers time concealed from him Mines therein so rich, that after his own happy discovery, one of them many yeers produced to him one hundred pounds <hi>sterling</hi> by the week, in Refined Silver, besides Lead to a good value. From whence may easily be inferred, that if you shall all prove cordial in this so great and good a Work, you may highly advance the honour and riches of our Country, and employ many thousands of poor men in an honest Labour, with good Wages, to support their Families, which now want employment.</p>
            <p>The consideration whereof, hath moved his Highness the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> further graciously to promise to the said <hi>Thomas Bushel</hi> all other assistances that his honourable Councel shall hereafter conceive conducible to the perfecting of so hopeful, publike, and pious a Work.</p>
            <p>And the said <hi>Thomas Bushel</hi> doth hereby declare, that if it shall please the Almighty to prosper him in this his underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, that he shall then provide a certain convenient Place, and skilfull Artists, for the tryal and perfecting of all such Natural Experiments, as have been imparted to him by his said honoured Lord and Master: and in the mean time, he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199121:13"/> hath prepared a Place very convenient, in <hi>Lambeth-Marsh;</hi> to which house, all persons concerned may direct their Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, to be assayed and tryed at the charge of me.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>Richard P.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHereas our late deceased Father <hi>Oliver Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector</hi> of happy memory, did by his Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents under the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> grant unto <hi>Thomas Bushel</hi> Esq; and his Coadventurers, all such Mines Royall as he or they should discover within this Commonwealth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving one fifth part thereof; And did also confirme his grant from the late King for the coyning of the Silver ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted out of his Mines; and whereas the said <hi>Tho. Bushel</hi> hath humbly remonstrated unto us, that he hath bin at a great charge and expence in making of Addits and Swallows for the draining of Sir <hi>Bevis Bulmars</hi> deserted lead Mines in Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits and green Oare, on the Forrest of <hi>Mendyp,</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerset,</hi> and doubts not by God's assistance, to effect the same in a short time, if he be not impeded therein by some malitious and dissolute persons, who (as appears to us by se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Affidavits) have already attempted to destroy the same; Wee, having received very good testimony of his abilities in Mineral affairs, and of his remarkable successes in following the Philosophical directions of his late Master the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor <hi>Bacon,</hi> and taking notice of the several Orders and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the grand Jury of <hi>Chewton,</hi> dated the 28 of <hi>May</hi> 1657, and the 28 of <hi>July</hi> 1658 for the regulating of the Miners there, and the incouraging of the said <hi>Tho Bushel</hi> in his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, Doe hereby ratifie and confirme the said Orders and Decrees, and by these presents streightly prohibit and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid all persons whatsoever to hinder or molest the said <hi>Tho. Bushel,</hi> his servants or workmen, or any of them in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings therein; And do require all Justices of Peace, Mayors, Sheriffs, Bayliffs, Constables and other Officers, and all our Colonells, Captains, Officers and Soldiers of our Army to assist the said <hi>Tho. Bushel</hi> and his Coadventurers against all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199121:14"/> violences and injuries that shall be attempted to hinder or spoile his said undertakings, and to punish severely all such as shall offend the aforesaid Decrees and our Commands herein, according as the offence shall merit, and as enemies to the Peace, Honor and Profit of this Nation, and as we expect their performance hereof; so this shall be their Warrant for so doing. Given under our Signet at <hi>Whitehall</hi> this Fifth day of <hi>February,</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To the Supreame Authority of this Common-wealth, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The humble Remonstrance of <hi>Thomas Bushel.</hi> Esq;</head>
            <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
            <p n="1">1. THat his Mineral service, grounded on his Master the Lord St. <hi>Albons</hi> Philosophical Theory may prove so advantagious and transcendent to the profit and honor of this Commonwealth, that in time (if rightly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed) it may exonerate the groaning Subjects of a conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable part of their heavy Taxes, and take from future Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments the necessity of ponderous Impositions upon a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed People.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he can assure your Honors by the oaths of divers persons of quality, that this unparallel'd Lord in the autumn of his age did affirm to King <hi>James</hi> when he made him Vis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, That he much repeated he had not made Mineral Philosophy the darling study of his Youth, as well as the Laws of the Kingdom, conceiving that he might as a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher, thereby have as much advanced the Glory of God in discovering the secrets of his Hand Maid Nature, as the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of his Prince, and the profit of his Country, as a States man; concluding that if his Mineral Notions had by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment been brought to perfection in his life time, when he had the assistance of his Princes power and favor, for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199121:14"/> and endowment of his <hi>Solomons</hi> house (designed in his new <hi>Atlantis</hi>) he had not left so hopeful an Embrion to abortion through his the said intrusted <hi>Bushels</hi> weaknes, or future vicissitudes; And he doth also aver, that he was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by a grateful Zeal to his said Masters honor, and the Republick in this Mineral service; and somewhat the more in remembrance of this saying of that Lord, <hi>That most poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Expedients for the increment of a Princes coffers, had a strong influence upon the peoples purses; But innocent Mineral Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons came nearest the Idea of Divine bounty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He affirms, that by way of Mart he hath already deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to his late Highness <hi>Oliver Lord Protector,</hi> and many other persons of quality One hundred three pound pieces of Gold, for which he is to receive five and ten for one, when he shall advance 1000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per</hi> week in Gold or Silver out of the Mines of the Territories of this Commonwealth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That there hath been so many thousand Tuns of Lead transported since <hi>William</hi> the Conquerors time unrefined, as by Records do amount unto Seventy Millions, which had the Lord <hi>Bacons</hi> Philosophy been then known, as it is now to be practised, the Silver of every Tun would have produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced five pound at the least one with another, and in the whole it had advanced to the treasure of this Nation Three hundred and fifty Millions of pounds sterling, and if this can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted out of the poorest Lead, with no loss to any mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man, what will then the richer Mettals prove to the honor and profit of this Republick if discovered by a diligent search after my old Masters way, designed in the annexed Model of <hi>Hingston</hi> Down and other places markt out by that Lord to defray the charges of the one out of the profits of the other,</p>
            <p n="5">5. That I am approaching, for president sake, to some memorable Act, worthy the honor of this State. and the trial of the Lord <hi>Bacons</hi> Philosophy, upon the forlorn hope of that great Ingineer Sir <hi>Bevis Bulmer</hi>'s drowned and deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Works of <hi>Rowpits,</hi> after 10000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> were expended out
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199121:15"/> of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Purse to perfect the same, but could not.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That he hath already discovered such Copper Mines and Calamunt stones, as we need not be any more obliged to foreign Nations, if your countenance will but quicken the ingenuity of Domestick Industry for securing and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging those publick Spirits that must survive his actions; and intend to make the World their Heir.</p>
            <p>In a word, most honorable sirs, He hath heard for truth, that the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon</hi> discoursing upon this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject before King <hi>James</hi> and the then Spanish Ambassador, said, <q>That if those two Princes would please to call their great Councils, &amp; to depute the extracted knowledge of all former Ages into one man, his Lordship did not doubt but in the notion of his own Philosophy to exceed them all for the future, both in easing the charges of Mineral discoveries, and their separating qualities for half the value, as well as the more certainty to find out their obscure Lodgings in their Mother Earth, then yet hath been promulged or practised by any; and that this Nation should not need to envy the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Silver Mines in America, which did much quicken my affections being a younger Brother of Fortune to search after the <hi>Meander</hi> of Natures Minerals.</q> For know, this is the fourth time I have laid my Reputation in the dust, and given it as many happy resurrections by my Mineral discoveries, be pleased therefore to afford me the honor of your Justice to protect my innocent Actions accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my Articles, that your deep intellects may the more transparently discern the miraculous mineral game plaid now by Providence more clearly to manifest my Lords Philosophy; That Sirs, out of worse then in a manner nothing in my self, and out of those drowned and forsaken Works, reputed to be the ruine of most Adventurers these forty years, he should by putting my Lords Receipts into Acts, produce such store of treasure as to maintain a Mint in your City of <hi>Wells.</hi> And whether this my obliged performance, if once pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199121:15"/> to the Model of this my humble Remonstrance, may not be an Emblem of a providential honor to perpetuate your Name, I shall humbly submit to your own wisdomes after your honours have vouchsaft to peruse the insuing lines, what a Mine Royal is known to be, and so resolved by the learned Lawyers of this Nation. And lastly, for that his Lordship would often say, That no person could pretend interest in Gold or Silver by the Law of Nations but the Sovereign Prince, lest a Subject might contest with the Seigniory of his Prerogative power through discovering such concealed Treasure within his barren and contemptible Herbage, nor that ever any Prince denied the assistance of his power to the poorest of his Servants, when Providence and Industry hath found in his own Territory such Ingredients to the Diadem of his Crown: Be pleased therefore in your clemency to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider these my humble Addresses of so high concernment upon your own Pillows, and so resolve whether I shall obey your commands as your Votary, or your Miner, and either shall please</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The humblest of your Servants,</hi> Tho. Bushel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="case">
            <head>The Case of a Mine Royal judged to be by the most learned Lawyers under their Hands.</head>
            <p>ALthough the Gold or Silver contained in the base Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of a Mine in the Land of a Subject, be of less value then the baser Mettall, yet if the Gold or Silver do counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail the charge of the refining it, or be of more worth then the base Mettal spent in refining it, this is a Mine Royal, and as well the base Mettal as the Gold and Silver in it belongs by Prerogative to the Crown.</p>
            <closer>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:199121:16"/>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Ralph Whitefield</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Serjeant at Law.</item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Edward Herbert</hi> Attorney General.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Oliver St. John</hi> Solicitor Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Orlando Bridgman</hi> the Parlia. Solicitor.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Glanvil</hi> Serjeant.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich. Creswel</hi> Serjeant.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Wilde</hi> Serjeant.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rob. Holborn.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Hern.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward Bagshaw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Lane.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard King.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edmund Prideaux.</hi>
                        <abbr>Esqs</abbr>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Maynard.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward Hide.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Glynne.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Charls Fulwood.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Harbottle Grimstone.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John White.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Peard.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Franklin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Weston.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Glover.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Ellis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Culpepper.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Goodwine.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Sanford.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John George.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ja. Haward,</hi>
                        <abbr>Esqs</abbr>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:199121:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199121:17"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199121:17"/>
            <head>M<seg rend="sup">R.</seg> Bushel's MINERALL OVERTURES.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to your commands, I do here present your Lordships with a brief Narrative of the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celor <hi>BACONS</hi> directions to my self, for the management of his Mineral experiments, in case his own Death should stop his intended progress there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, before he could practically discover the true ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and spreading qualities of Minerals, I being then his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Servant.</p>
            <p>King <hi>JAMES</hi> having already promised to grant his Lordship all his own discoveries of Mines Royal, and also of any drowned Lands, or deserted Works, by him to be recovered within the space of Forty years, paying him the fifth, according to the usual custome of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> in his Mines of the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> and of other Princes, after the expiration of Fourteen years first granted <hi>gratis</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the great charge of his new Invention, to facillitate the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Mineral Riches of this Land, occasioned by a learned Speech his Lordship hath lately made to his Majesty, [Count <hi>GƲNDA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MORE,</hi> and divers of the Nobility being present.] concerning the rise, and magnificent growth of the <hi>China</hi> Trade; wherein by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect demonstration he made it appear, that the invention of one man (by his helping the defects of Nature, with the Materials of Art, and the patience of three Ages industrie to bring its concoction to perfection) became the great Revenew of that Empire, and hath bin for this thousand years the only honor of that people, as well as their livelyhood and Patrimonie.] In which he seriously protested, That his utmost ambition in the affairs of this World affected no greater glory, then to leave the real fruits of his best service to his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, Honor to his Name, his written Works to Posterity, and by such Treasures as his own Industrie should raise out of his Mineral experiments, to accomplish the noble Design and Fabrick of his <hi>SOLOMONS</hi> House, described in his new Atlantis annexed to his Natural Historie; seeing that the Corporation of the Mines Royal, instituted by his Majesty, consisting of Lords and Gentlemen of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199121:18"/> produced but weak, or very small advantages to the Revene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Crown, or the publick good; although his Lordship did then really believe it very possible for himself (if qualified thereto by his regall Power) to bring it so to pass in one Age, that the barrenest Mountains in this Nation should produce such store of Treasure by their Royall Veines; as we need not envie the King of <hi>Spain's</hi> felicitie in his <hi>Potezi,</hi> or any other Mines in <hi>America;</hi> and thereupon by way of similitude added this, That as a State, whose present dimensions were but small, might happily serve as a foundation for an ample Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, if all regard of private propriety were laid aside, and every Member thereof would diligently devote his particular care to the publick ben fit; even so it might happen in the advancement of the discoveries of those Mineral Riches supposed to lie hid in the bosomes of the most barren Mountains, when the whole industrie of the many several persons employed, should be concentrick in that service, and act as the united faculties of one man, their hearts being free from all ends and ambitious thoughts, save such as conduced to Gods glory and the common good. But so soon as his Lordship had vouchsafed to acquaint me concerning his proceedings with his Majesty in this Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, he bad me call to mind the many fatherly favors which he had conferred upon me, as pious motives to retard my unripe years from hazardous travels; and having professed to his Lordship, that I could not with any content resolve to live in my Native Country, ever since I understood, that younger Brothers by the Law of the Land were not participant in their Fathers Inheritance, but that they were by the ways of Vertue and Industrie, to attend the Almighties bounty, for acquiring such fortunes as primogeniture had conferred upon their elder Brothers, or otherwise to live in an inferior or servile condition; and then instanced his acceptance of me for his servant at fifteen years of age, upon my own Address; his clearing all my debts three several times, with no smaller sum in the whole then Three thousand pound, his preferring me in Marriage to a rich Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retrix, and thereupon not only allowing me Four hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> but to ballance the consent of her Father in the Match, promised upon his honor to make me the Heir of his knowledge, in Mineral Philosophy, saying▪ That if those reall expressions of his love could but find the due retalliation of my gratitude, he might then assure himself of the hoped Harvest of two Lives in one; infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that although Fathers are bound to provide for their Children, and worse then Infidels if they do not, yet there is no such injunction upon Masters, in relation to their Servants; and therefore where a Masters pious bounty transcends a Fathers naturall love, there that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199121:18"/> so obliged servant must appear most prodigiously ingratefull, which shall not with much zeal and faithfulness, discharge the duty of a sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving Trust; seriously adding this: <hi>Bushel,</hi> I must now use you, my intended instrument, in the prosecution of my Mineral Designs, as politick Princes do their nearest servants in their Cabinet-Counsels; who putting their Masters conceptions into act, if they take well with the people, must own no more of them then the approbation thereof, and the admiration of their Princes wisdom therein; but in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary effect (to salve their Princes honor) they must sadly acknowledge the matter wholly their own; an Error in their Counsels, and a crime in themselves: so you, if by my Theorie you prosper in your practick, must attribute all the honor of the whole work to me; if otherwise, you must gratefully preserve my reputation, by acknowledging your own misfortune, in mistaking and misacting my directions, and so you shall be sure to gain the Title and Character of a grateful servant in either event. And upon my serious protestation, that I would faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obey all his Commands, his Lordship advised me, not to follow the practice of our Predecessors, in their tedious and expensive ways of sinking Ayrie shafts at every forty fathoms, nor to imitate the antient <hi>Romans,</hi> by digging Mines through deep and open Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; but by cutting <hi>Addits</hi> into the Mountains at their lowest Level, and by supplying their defect of Aire with <hi>Pipe</hi> and <hi>Bellows,</hi> being an invention utterly unknown to former Ages. And for my first experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to begin with those five Mountains in <hi>Cardiganshire,</hi> reported by Sir <hi>FRANCIS GODOLPHIN,</hi> and a <hi>Portugues,</hi> to be rich in Silver and Lead. But if I should by my practick part faile in my deeper search, either for want of convenient Aire, or a suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Vein of Ore, his Lordship commanded me to pursue his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in that particular no further; yet if my happy success should prove his Theorie true in this, as also in the several ways of separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Mettle from the Dross, and the Silver from the Lead, that then I should not faile to illustrate the innocent Trade of the poor Miners, by making his Lordship the Patron of their Profession, nor neglect to dedicate the whole profit which Divine Providence should reveale in the one, to find out the Riches of the other; and above all, that I should take speciall care to elect such honest Agents for the carrying on this innocently profitable work, as their vertuous ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons should aime at no by respect beyond the publick good of their Country, they having a competent salary for their modest mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: But these <hi>Embrions</hi> proving abortive, by the death of that Lord in the Reigne of King <hi>James,</hi> where the sad motive which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199121:19"/> my pensive retirements to a three years sollitude, untill di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence calling me to a more active life, I discovered and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Natures ingenious designs upon my Rock at <hi>Enston</hi> in <hi>Oxford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> by making it such a delightfull <hi>Grotto,</hi> that the same of it invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the late King <hi>Charls</hi> to a voluntary visit: By which means I not only became known to his Majesty, but also found an apt occasion to discourse the above mentioned Proposals of the Lord <hi>BACONS</hi> Philosophy, who so well approved of my Ingenie upon that place, and his Lordships Mineral Model, that he presently promised me the assistance of his Mint, according to the president of other Princes, when I should find silver worth the coyning; and likewise the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation of my own Lead so discovered, Custom, free for 21. years, as also my choise of renting the whole Custom of that Comodity at the rate of the Farmers Books, calculated by the account of seven years Audit, to put the speculations of my Masters Theory into practice. These high favors of the late King conferred on my self, in memory of that Lords eminent abilities, and this his admonition (before the Earl of <hi>Dorset</hi>) to me at <hi>York:</hi> That if (in the War then like to ensue) I should not prove real, and active in his service, and cordial in the trust reposed in me by my <hi>quondam</hi> Lord, I should justly me: it the Title and reputation of a Knave; which did then provoke me forwards in my undertakings, with a most zealous observation of my oblieged fidelity to both, till his Majesty (at <hi>CAƲSAM</hi>) dis-ingaged me in the first, that he might enable me as much as in him say, to perform the latter, by his gracious letter of permission to surrender <hi>Lundy</hi> at my own charge fortified and maintained, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out injury or violence to any) upon such Articles as might take off my delinquency, and restore me to my Estate, and the grants of my Mines, Mints, and Customes, rather then the fore mentioned design so well digested by my honorable Lord, for the general good, should be made frustrate by my incapacity to prosecute; I being the only man made privy to all those his Mineral speculations, and some other of his Philosophical Lucubrations, not yet to be promulged, until my proficiency and success in the Min s shall enable me thereto; since he, in the depth of his wisdom, thought it not only the harmlessest gaine and greatest good that could befall a Commonwealth, but also found it to be the chiefest study and industry of the most knowing and best bred persons of other Nations, and the highest and most Honorable improvement that this world was capable of, and I protest, as in the presence of God, (such a progress I have already made herein) that if I could now command as much wealth as ever the Lydian <hi>Croesus</hi> did possess, I would gladly adventure it all in perforating the barren
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199121:19"/> Mountains, to discover the vast Treasures which lie hid in their Rocky entrails, for the good of this Nation, and to leave after my debts paid a magnificent Monument in memory of my most deserving Master, by finishing his <hi>SOLOMONS</hi> House in all its dimensions, and with all the accommodations and endowments thereof, according to his Lordships own Heroick <hi>Idea;</hi> if the honorable Parliament sh ll be pleased to ratifie my Articles, I having already by his direction cut through five of the 28 Mountains at the lowest Level, which his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and Sir <hi>FRANCIS GODOLPHIN</hi> did mark out as the most pregnant Hills, for discovering the Beds, and spreading Branches of this Nations Mineral Treasures: so that no man of known judgment, but must conclude the rest to be of the same <hi>species,</hi> or of richer natures, in their deeper search both for quantity and quality; and how happy a success the great God of Nature hath given to my endeavors in this particular, <hi>the ensuing Letter, sent from</hi> Mr. Brod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, a learned and judicious Divine, and one constantly resident a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Miners, <hi>will better speak, then any Pen whatsoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THOMAS BUSHELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A LETTER to Mr. <hi>BƲSHELL,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating some strange accidents, which happened in the MINES.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honored Sir;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SUffer my congratulations of your late success at <hi>Tallybont</hi> to be admitted among the rest, who have represented the same to your imagination: not so much for the historical report of it, as for speculation on it; So it becomes my quality, for the rest are interessed, I, a looker on your <hi>Addit</hi> or great drift of <hi>Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libont:</hi> after above <hi>400</hi> fathome in four years driving to come at the chief shaft of the old drowned work of <hi>38</hi> fathome deep, being pierced by the water of the old work, <hi>June 27</hi> at midnight there befell two memorable accidents. The four workmen about one in the night (as their manner was) withdrew to take Tobacco with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199121:20"/> ten fathome of the <hi>Addits</hi> mouth, least in the fore-field it should damp the aire, which was conveyed to them by your leaden Pipes with Bellowes. Their smoakie banquet was not yet at an end, when they heard a mighty and fearful noise, which some of them said was thunder. But old <hi>Bartholmew Clocker</hi> (a well-experienced <hi>Miner</hi>) although he left the work without any suspition of so near an approach re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olved suddenly, the work is holed, come let us away. No sooner had they gotten the free aire, but out gusheth the torrent of water with an incredible fury, such a breach it made in the solid Rock, that it arose a full yards height at the <hi>Addits</hi> mouth, and drove away above <hi>100</hi> Tun of the rockie deads, affrighting the people of <hi>Tallybont,</hi> who heard the noise and felt the water in their houses. I do not remember that I was ever more astonish'd at the prodigiousness of any spectacle, to see what perdition was threatned to the poor men, and they so to escape it. About four hours after the violence of water being past, <hi>Fisher</hi> one other of the <hi>Miners</hi> went in with more curiosity then wit, to see what effect it had wrought there: and being some sixtie fathome in, creeping very low, his candle enkindled a vapor, which came on him with three or four flashes, and he suddainly returning had his hair burnt off, and his clothes scorched, in which conclusion it gave a crack like the report of a Peice, and in a fierce gust of wind blew out the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles of three more coming after him. To omit the Philosophical inquisition of natural causes, I account his preservation in as high a degree of wonder as the first. Thus happy are you here when least you think of it, for I find the Subterranean spirits, the supposed Guardians of concealed treasure, as officious for you as if they were in pay with you. But in a stile more proper to my pen, Behold Sir, how dear you are to providence, which for your sake hath vouchsafed to digress into a Miracle, and such a one as is able to convert the most Sophistical <hi>Athe st;</hi> whence your piety will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, that the gracious Author of this incomparable bounty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects from you some grateful service, as high above ordinary (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to mortal capacity) as this favor hath been extraordinary. We are all deeply in the same engagement, and have learned by this experiment, that these <hi>Addits</hi> or approaches (for that's the sence of the name of old Deluge works) are attempts of despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199121:20"/> hazzard. Me thinks those Mountains are as so many pregnant Wombs, and now in labour call for your fortunate hands to deliver them, to the honor of your Royall Master, and perpetuated glory of the Nation.</p>
            <p>What should you doubt in an employment so serenely smild upon, by the highest both of Heaven and Earth? You use no inchantment, or magnetical Rod, to discover the veins, your only magick, is an ingenious conjecture of probabiliti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> with a chearful and indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable industry which hath hitherto succeeded beyond expectation of most, and (peradventure) the desires of some. But who, (as <hi>Agricola</hi> makes the question) that is not of a nature im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poison'd with envy and malitiousness,<note place="margin">Lib. 1. de R. M</note> can bear unfriendly thoughts to him, whose substance is in a manner presented by the hand of God.</p>
            <p>I know it would be a motive of very feeble operation, to tell you how Princes and States have raised their Crowns, by descending into such abysses as these; with some of whom wanton Antiquity hath been pleased to sport her self, and to play upon the simplicity of many, as <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Gyges,</hi> the <hi>Argonauts, C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oesus,</hi> with the States of <hi>Athens,</hi> over whose Minerals was that renowned <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cydides</hi> a <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aefect,</hi> as you are here. Of which, <hi>Pliny</hi> delivers what may be worth your attention, when he sayes of them, That they were in a fruitless soyle, and on the Hils (as these with us.) And wheresoever one vein was found, it was not far from another; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which was one called <hi>Bebelo,</hi> that afforded him <hi>300</hi> pound weight of Silver a day</p>
            <p>These were then the veins which conveyed the blood and spirit of life, through all the Limbs of his victorious Host. And have you not here our Britains <hi>Asturia</hi> before you? Who knows whether it may not yield a <hi>Bebelo?</hi> at least a <hi>Sneberg</hi> or <hi>Anneberg?</hi> Who hath heretofore dream't of a Mine at <hi>Comsomloch,</hi> or of the happy Lot you lately drew from the Mountains of <hi>Keginian, Tally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bont,</hi> the <hi>Darren, Broom-Floyd,</hi> and <hi>Cum-mervin?</hi> What did the outside of these promise you, more then the countenances of their Neighbors? But the Complaint of Learned <hi>D. Jourdan</hi> may here take place, that much Silver was lost for want of taking it out of Lead-Oares: for whereas those Oars which are rich in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199121:21"/> Silver, are commonly hard of fusion, our Mineral men neglect those Oars. No doubt many are concealed, by reason they are Mines Royall.</p>
            <p>Where had been the Woods and Forrests yet undestroyed on these bald-headed Promontories, that might suffice, had you not taught the Earth to afford you all, and the worthless Valley to meet the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Hill, by sending in Fewel to give forme to the matter? So that here is a rich bequest you leave to posterity, I mean your eternizing the Works, by preventing the excesse of Water, and defect of Fire, I have no more, but to signifie my confidence, that as your desires are set on the material Rocks of <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>Enstone,</hi> so will your better affections be firmly grounded upon the Rock <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> that no Tempest may be able to shake you, when the sandie Projects of other will be laved to nothing by the Flouds they are built upon: which will give more comfort and satisfaction to you, then can be expressed by your</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>True Friend and Servant, THOMAS BRODWAY.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Julii <hi>4. 1641.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199121:21"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To his Highness the Lord PROTECTOR of</hi> England, Scotland and Ireland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The humble Petition of the Proprietors, Commoners and Mineral Bounders of the Deserted and Drowned Mines within the Counties of <hi>Cornwal</hi> and <hi>Devon.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
            <p>THat your Petitioners observing the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental way of Mr. <hi>Bushell's</hi> Proceedings, to be not only the most probable to discover the vast Mineral-Treasure supposed to lie in the Metal-loads of that Beacon-Hill called <hi>Hingston-Down, Coome-Martin</hi> in <hi>Devon,</hi> and <hi>Guynop</hi> in <hi>Cornwal;</hi> But like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the onely probable means to enrich these Western parts, and your other Territories with inestimable treasure, by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his example in all drowned and deserted Works; And because we find he hath no more desire of Partnership then the assistance of Providence, and your Highness patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nising this his commendable Enterprise, nor any other am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition then gratitude to the memory of that great Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, his deceased Master, the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon,</hi> and to make our Age the president and honor of fulfilling the old proverb, <hi>Hingston-Down welly wrought, is worth London-Town dearey bought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in regard the Lords of the Fee, and Commoners thereof, as well as the major part of the Mineral bounders, have with all cheerful alacritie (for the publick good of this Nation) subscribed their affectionate Consents to this great Work, in a Letter to Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi> hereunto annexed:
<q>We your Petitioners do in the behalf of our selves and the Mineral Bounders of <hi>Cornwal</hi> and <hi>Devon,</hi> implore
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199121:22"/> your Highness speedy Confirmation of Mr. <hi>Bushell's</hi> Articles, without his personal attendance in <hi>London,</hi> according to the gracious signification of your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness favors to his Petition, that no time may be lost in so honorable a Design, nor he disabled or dismaid in so general a Concernment; since we find him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding active to study the preservation of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and Dignities, with the Countries advancement, as to your Highness wisdom may appear by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration of his Mineral Overtures, and a draught of his unanswerable Reasons likewise annexed.</q>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Charls Trevanion</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Mainard</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edw. Herle</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Chatley</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Tremenhere</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Phi. Lanyon</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edw. Wise</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Arundell</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fran. Buller jun.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ja. Launce</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>David Hawes</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chr. Wood</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Wise</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>J. Boscowen</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Lower.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Coryton</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Lampen</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Grose</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Fathers</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Wrey</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nath. Tarvanion</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Rous.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE have seriously considered the proffer'd Civilities in your Letter, and the plain Demonstrations in your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous Reasons, to cut North and South through the lowest Level of <hi>Hingston-Down,</hi> for crossing all such Metal-loads as lie East and West, and for freeing the Mines from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment of water; by which you may verefie the old pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Hingston-Down welly wrought, is worth London-Town dearey bought:</hi> And therefore you may rest assured, that we shall give our free consents and endevours to procure other Gentlemen of our County to further your most noble and unparralleld design, that a speedy dispatch may be made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199121:22"/> for the general good of the Nation, which is and shall be ever very much desired by</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novemb.</hi> 11. 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your very ready friends and Servants,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edw. Herle.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cha. Trevanion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>J. Boscowen:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chicheste Wr ey.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edw. Wise.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Wise.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Lampen.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ja. Launce.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Erisey.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Chatley.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Phi. Lanyon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Natha. Tarvanyon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hu. Pomeroy.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Grose.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Arundell.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Rous.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>N. Borlace.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Lower.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fran. Buller.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Coryton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Harris.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nich. Sharsell.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Battersby.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>J. Tremenhere</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Wrey.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Coysgrave.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward Wilcocks.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Fathers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>David Haws.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>For our Noble Friend <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> Esq; These.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Mr. <hi>Bushels</hi> Letter to the Miners of <hi>Mendyp,</hi> and their Answer, with the Juries Order.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Fellow Miners,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>UPon the Overtures of my Mineral Discoveries taught me by the Theory of my old Master the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon's</hi> Philosophical Conceptions; His Highness the Lord Protector upon hopes of the like providence in all his other Territories to ease the Nation of their Taxes, gave me power to try the aforesaid Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, since it was conceived by the aforesaid Lord, that great riches lay in the Bowels of our Mother Earth, and underneath the superficies of the most barren Mountains; and in order to such his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199121:23"/> commands, I have not onely published the inclosed declaration for satisfaction to all moderate persons, which have not unbyassed Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples against the honor of their native Country, but also am setting on foot the drowned and deserted works in the naked Promento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngston Down, Coom-Martine</hi> in <hi>Devon,</hi> and <hi>Guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nop</hi> in <hi>Cornwal:</hi> And being likewise informed by your fellow Miners, that Millions of wealth lie in <hi>Rowpit</hi> neer <hi>Chewton</hi>-Minery, which yet cannot be recovered from the inundation of water by the greatest Artists of former Ages: I have upon my own delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and viewing the place, thought fit to render you the experience of my practical endeavors, and with a willing mind to attempt the Forelorn hope of their recoveries at my own charge, if I may have the well-wishes of you in general, and the moyety or half, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equal charge, when the water is drained your speedy answer shall make me decline or prosecute the same with effect, which is the only ambition of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithful Friend, <hi>T. B.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April <hi>21. 1657.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>For his very loving Friends,</hi> John Phelps, Tho. Voules, Will. Cole, Alex. Jett, Will. Betten, Rob. Radford, <hi>and</hi> Tho. Wood, <hi>with the rest, these deliver.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worshipful,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MAnna from Heaven was not more welcome to the Pilgrims of <hi>Israel,</hi> then the good news your Letter brought to us poor Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of <hi>Mendyp,</hi> who now are like <hi>Moses</hi> in the Mount, which saw the Land of Promise, and yet could not enjoy the propriety thereof; even so fares it now with us: For a month or two of a droughty Summer we behold the appearance of much treasure lying in the veins of those metal Loads, and so soon as we are preparing for Harvest, to reap a mite of its Mineral profit, the inundation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199121:23"/> of water takes away our present possession, and leaves us exposed to a sad condition, having no other Profession for our livelihood. But if your goodness and charity will be pleased to extend the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of your knowledge to drain the Rake called the Broad Rake of Sir <hi>Bevis Bulmars</hi> Works in <hi>Rowpits</hi> near <hi>Chewton</hi> Minery, which is known to be the lowest Level, and Sole of those Works; We do herein engage our selves under our hands and Seals, and on the behalf of all others that shall hereafter work in the said Rake, that you and your Assigns shall have the moyety of the whole, paying half the charge; and likewise procure the Lord of the Soil to do the like, if you please to proceed with speed for the perfecting of the same; and in token of our affection to serve you, we have presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not onely to petition his Highness in your behalf for the better encouragement, but also oblige our selves to tender you the first refusal of all our parts and shares of Oar, paying ready money, and giving us from time to time the same rate as other Merchants shall conceive it to be worth: And so we bid you heartily farewel, resting</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>May <hi>2. 1657.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your ever obliged Servants,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Valen Tryme,</hi> for his part.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. White.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioh. Hoskins.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Andrew Baller.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nich. Barrel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Blackhouse.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Johnsons.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Norman.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Thrisel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Atwood</hi> sen.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Naish.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edw. Hopkins.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nich. Plumley.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Hinsh.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich. Friar.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jam. Midleham.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Phelps.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Voules.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Cole.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rob. Clark</hi> sen.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rob. Clark</hi> jun.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Voules.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Atwood</hi> jun.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Alex. Jett.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Rowles.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nich. Parker.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Dudden.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Radford.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rob. Radford.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>For</hi> Tho. Bushel, <hi>Esq;</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:199121:24"/>
            <head>Chewton-Jury, May <hi>28. 1657.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHereas we of this Mineral Grand Jury are credibly informed of the great design for the publike good of the Miners, which do adventure in <hi>Rowpits,</hi> and is now undertaken by <hi>Tho. Bushel</hi> Esq; which were formerly the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted Works left by Sir <hi>Bevis Bulmar</hi> in the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, and whereas many of the chief Adventurers in the said <hi>Rowpits</hi> do and have consented to surrender the one half of their Works and Mines there unto the said <hi>Tho. Bushel</hi> and his Assigns, when the said <hi>Tho. Bushel</hi> doth make it appear, that by his or their Workmanship they be freed of the inundation of their Waters, unto the Mineral Court for the time being: We of this Jury do order and make this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, that when it shall happen that the said <hi>Tho. Bushel</hi> doth prove that he hath by his Workmanship done by him and his Assigns, cleared any Miners work as aforesaid, unto the Jury as aforesaid, he shal enjoy the one half of the Works: Provided alwaies, the said <hi>Tho. Bushel</hi> and they shall be liable to pay all Mineral costs and charges, as far as he and they are entrusted, agreeable to the custom and Law of the Occupation; and to this we all agree, and have subscribed our hands, the day and year first above written.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Andrew Baller.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Phelps.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Attwood</hi> sen.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nich. Barrel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Norman.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nich. Parker.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Io. Cornish.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edw. Hopkins.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Dudden.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Rowles.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Blackhouse.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John House.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Hoskins.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Thristle.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Johnsons.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Attwood</hi> jun.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nich. Plumley.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Valen Dudden.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:199121:24"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To his Highness the Lord Protector of</hi> England, Scotland and Ireland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The humble Petition of the Mineral-Bounders within the County of <hi>Somerset.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
            <p>THat your Petitioners observing the experimental way of Mr. <hi>Pushell's</hi> proceedings to recover the vast Mineral Treasure known to lie in the drowned and deserted Works of that antient Forrest called <hi>Mendyp-hill;</hi> And being like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the onely probable means to enrich your other Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, by following his example in concealed places of the like nature:
<q>We your Petitioners do in the behalf of our selves, and the generalitie of laborious Miners, who have no other subsistence then Providence in those harmless affairs, humbly implore your Highness confirmation of Mr. <hi>Bushell's</hi> Articles without his personal attendance, that no time may be lost in such an honorable concernment; since his active diligence in that Mineral proceed is to study the preservation of the Poor's livelihood under ground, as well as the riches, honor and profit it may afford to the Nation by this his invention, according to your Highness trust reposed in him for that purpose, as appears by the demonstrative Reasons of his Mineral Overtures.</q>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:199121:25"/>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Grand-Jury for the Libertie of the Castle of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> upon the Forrest of <hi>Mendyp.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Radford</hi> Foreman</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Colliar</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Spiring</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Midell</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Liget</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Ames</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Roger Tegg</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich. Harris</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Walter Hoads</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will Fry</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Vowles</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mich. Curtis</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hen. Hutchins</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Chapman</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Barrell</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Barrell</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>And. Spirrin</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Bates</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Bush</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Haydon</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Haydon</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich. Haydon</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Chyles</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich. Filer</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Geo. Filer</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Canby</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Tucker</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Tucker</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Na. Brown</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Bary</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Martin</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Hyden</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Andrew Bath</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sam. Cox</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Tegg</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Blackman</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Anth. Eggesfield</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Harris.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Grand-Jury for the Libertie of <hi>Charterhouse-Hydon</hi> upon the Forrest of <hi>Mendyp.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Radford</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Brown</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mat. Chansler</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Plumley</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter Herler</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Leonard Fox</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Geo. Colse</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Bluning</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Tucker</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Lane sen.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Lane</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich. Thomas Clark</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Lane jun.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Geo. Whithead</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Chansler</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fra. Ozer</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Walter Thutchen</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Brock</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Geo. Tucker</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Cole</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Blackman</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Blackman</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Waker</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Geo. Hoskins.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:199121:25"/>
            <head>Mr. Basbee's <hi>Affidavit.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>VVAlter Basbee</hi> aged about eighty years, maketh oath, That he was Saymaster to <hi>Goldsmiths Hall</hi> about fifty years ago, and vers'd in Minerals ever since both at home and abroad, and was by King <hi>James</hi> sent to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of <hi>Russia</hi> to make him a Standard of Gold and Silver in his Mint in the City of <hi>Moscovia,</hi> equivalent to the Tower of <hi>London;</hi> And no sooner was that service performed by this Deponent, but his Imperial Majesty commanded him to refine the Gold of a rich Copper-mine lying in <hi>Cyberea,</hi> five hundred miles beyond the river <hi>Volgo,</hi> which held of Gold in every Tun to the value of three, four, or five hundred pounds; where this Deponent did remain until he was taken prisoner by the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and afterwards exchanged by the Emperor to be sent for <hi>England;</hi> where this Deponent hath ever since spent most of his time, under Mr. <hi>Bushell's</hi> Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophical way, taught him by the late Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon,</hi> which (in the judgment of this Deponent) cannot be paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd by any, and if now practised according to his printed Remonstrance, and the Mineral Grand-Jury's Order of <hi>Chew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> this Deponent doth verily believe that the Age we live in will exceed all former Ages in Mineral Discoveries and their Separations.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Walter Basbee.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sworne the</hi> 7. <hi>of December</hi> 1658. <hi>before me one of the Masters of Chancery in ordinary,</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>W. Glascock.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:199121:26"/>
            <head>Christopher Wright's <hi>Affidavit.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>CHristopher Wright</hi> aged fifty six years maketh oath, That he was sent by Mr. <hi>Joseph Hexeter</hi> of <hi>Cumberland</hi> to be in the same place of Steward for direction of Mr. <hi>Bushels</hi> Minerals under ground, as the said Mr. <hi>Hexeter</hi> was under him in <hi>Wales</hi> at 100 <abbr>l.</abbr>
               <hi>per ann.</hi> salary: And finding the said Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi> to give such probable reasons for recovering the inundation of water out of the vast and drowned Works of <hi>Rowpits,</hi> by persuing a Drift as a Common-shore, from the Concaves of a natural swallow twenty fathom deep, after his industrie had sunk twenty shafts to discover the same, on purpose to come to the rich loads of metal known to be buried in the adjacent groves of water: This Deponent and others, upon confidence of making good his great under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings therein (although his judgment was then much questioned by the Inhabitants for the attempt) did and do desire but half wages ever since the Miners of <hi>Mendip</hi> had invited the said Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi> under their hands and Decree of their Court, to have half the profit, bearing half the charge, after the water was drained, which this Deponent doth verily believe will be in a short time perfected, and appear for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent sake, as well as for present profit, the greatest work that hath been done by any Mineralist these hundred years, if the malicious attempts of some ill-natured persons do not now hinder the growth of his proceedings therein: For this Deponent doth depose, that by some wicked persons there was a great Lake of muddy water turned about the hour of midnight, and upon a great flood, into the Swallow, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose as is conceived to choak it, and so consequently to drown his men that came from forein parts, and were then work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing twenty fathom deep, which this Deponent doth aver were forced to save their lives by running up their grooves at the same time, the swallow being not able to receive the torrent of its water. And this Deponent doth likewise de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199121:26"/> That about the 10. of <hi>October</hi> last there was some other such envious person who pulled down so much of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timber of his Shaft, that the whole groove of earth fell into Mr. <hi>Bushels</hi> Drift, when his men were at work underneath; and it was supposed by divers never to be recovered: But thanks be to God, the danger is past, and Mr. <hi>Bushels</hi> Drift goeth on towards the rich works known to lie 150 fathom before him; for this Deponent was one of the workmen that landed 100<hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per</hi> week out of one Shaft this last summer, and saw 200<hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per</hi> week out of another; but the charge of drawing water, though in the drought of summer, stood (as they reported) in 80 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per</hi> week apeece, which Mr. <hi>Bushels</hi> Drift will prevent; and likewise to 1000 more of the like nature as are supposed to be within the verge of <hi>Rowpits.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Christopher Wright.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sworne the</hi> 3. <hi>of December</hi> 1658. <hi>before me one of the Masters of Chancery in ordinary,</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>W. Glascock.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Testimony of some Miners of <hi>Mendyp</hi> to the Council.</head>
            <p>WE whose names are hereunder written, being Miners, and well vers'd in the Mineral Rakes of <hi>Rowpits</hi> upon the Forrest of <hi>Mendyp,</hi> are ready to testifie upon oath, That the great wrongs done to the works of <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> Esq; in <hi>Rowpits,</hi> as is deposed by <hi>Christopher Wright</hi> before a Master of Chancery, are of a certain truth; And we are likewise ready to testifie our opinions upon oath, That if the way of Mr. <hi>Bushels</hi> now proceeding to recover those drowned and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199121:27"/> deserted works, may go on without molestation, according to the Orders of the Grand Jury of <hi>Chewton</hi> made for his encouragement, we do believe in our consciences that there hath not been these hundred years such a service done to this Commonwealth, in advancing the knowledge of the Miners trade, for profit and precedent. And we also humbly conceive, that if a binding Order be made by your Lordships to confirm (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n all points) the said Grand Jury of <hi>Chewton's</hi> Orders for deferring unrulie Miners from such exorbitancies, as also that no persons should lose any more their Summers work to follow the Mines of <hi>Rowpits</hi> (which are now to no more purpose in matter of profit, then to wash the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moor) until Mr. <hi>Bushels</hi> Drift can come up to drain their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation of waters, which (as we find exprest in his Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance) he doth undertake to perfect in four years; and we do verily believe, that not only all the Oar may be then land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for two shillings <hi>per</hi> Tun, but that we shall then also know the inestimable riches of that place without further charge, or ruining more families in working upon <hi>Rowpits.</hi> And we do also confidently believe in our consciences, that when Mr. <hi>Bushels</hi> now Drift from his Swallow doth come up to the old works drowned, and that he doth pursue likewise his Cross-Rake from his Swallow to the forebreast of Sir <hi>Bevis Bulmars</hi> deserted work, (as he saith he intends to do, so soon as he hath secured the place according to agreement, and the Grand Jury's Order of <hi>Chewton</hi> dated the 28. of <hi>May</hi>) the said Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi> will make good his Marqus of a Thousand pounds <hi>per</hi> week: For there are men yet alive that will ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie, that the forebreast of Sir <hi>Bevis Bulmar's</hi> work was nine foot wide in oar; and we our selves know, that a hundred pounds <hi>per</hi> week out of one Groove in the old work is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, when the suffocation of water doth not hinder them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Bakehouse</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Bakehouse</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Doxie.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199121:27"/>
            <head>Chewton <hi>28</hi> of July, <hi>1658.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHereas wee of the Mineral grand Jury finding by a decretal Order of our Predecessors <hi>May</hi> 28, and their Letter <hi>May</hi> 2 in answer of <hi>Tho. Bushell's</hi> Esq; to incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage him to go on in his adventures for recovering the drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed works of <hi>Rowpits,</hi> which were formerly the deserted works of Sir <hi>Bevis Bulmar</hi> in the time of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Reign. And whereas many of the chief Adventurers in the said <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits,</hi> do and have consented to surrender not only the one half of their works and Mines there, but likewise the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption of the other half, paying as much as any other Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant willl give, unto the said <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> and his Assigns, when the said <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> doth make it appear unto the Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Court for the time being, that by his and their workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship they be freed from the inundation of their waters. Wee of the grand Jury do Order and confirm the said Decree. And whereas wee find the said <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> hath (in relation to his undertakings of recovering their waters) brought it so near a probability of perfection, that in time all persons of known Judgement cannot but conclude the same will be done for the general good of those that had formerly suffered by those Grooves, and likewise a president for others to follow the like example, as also the certainty of knowing the vast riches that lie in <hi>Rowpits</hi> and Green Oare: And whereas wee are informed by the said <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> and others, of several misdemeanors committed against him by turning floods into his swallow, to choak and extirpate all his proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, stealing of his tooles from his works, depraving of his Person with scandalous language, and making new pitches in <hi>Rowpits</hi> before him, so soon as they saw the forefield of Mr. <hi>Bushell's</hi> Drift from his Swallow had but a vein of ground Oare, 4 foot wide; and 3 fathom high to cherish his chargeable undertakings, which uncivill actions of theirs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199121:28"/> were as we conceive contrary to all equity and good consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and in a manner an Act of syranny in us, that Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi> should drain our waters; and wee should suffer stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to take the benefit of new pitches from his adventures, to recover such drowned and forsaken works as the greatest Engineer hath deserted, when all persons have the whole Hill of <hi>Mendyp</hi> to make their fortunes by such pitches, as he alledgeth, and not to discourage his desperate undertakings therein by such malitious practices, and especially to such a person as Mr. <hi>Bushell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that is sent by his Highness the Lord Protector, to recover such drowned and deserted works for the publick good of the Nation, with power to dig, delve, and search in the several grounds of all his Territories by Letters Patents, paying double trespass, aswell as in all vast Commons, upon hopes from such experiments to ease in time the Taxes of the Subject, and to give new birth to the drooping condition of a Miners profession; Wee of the grand Jury of <hi>Chewton</hi> (and other Workmasters and Miners) for the reasons aforesaid, and for preventing any just com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Lord Paramount against our Lord Royall's Court of <hi>Chewton</hi> for such incivilities to the person which his Highness hath trusted in that affair, do Order and make this Decree (for the said <hi>Tho. Bushell's</hi> better incouragement) That from the day of the date of the Order <hi>May</hi> 28, all such new pitches shall be void in <hi>Rowpits</hi> and Green oare, but such as the said <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> shall approve and allow of; and that all former works that have been wrought upon within these 5 years, and sunk 5 fathom deep, to stand good by consent, provided that they keep them lawful, and sink them to the water, when the said <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> is come near them with his Drift of 16 fathom deep by the approbation of this grand Jury, that so the wilfulness of any malitious person might not hinder such a proceed to know the Meanders of those Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rakes in their deepor search, and the way to go to their recoveries, for their own good aswell as Mr. <hi>Bushell's</hi> reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the attempt of that great design. And whereas the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199121:28"/> said <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> doth aver, that he never did intend to make it a Mine-Royall by his Art and Skill (to the prejudice of us, our Laws and Liberties) as it was reported, unless it were against the interest of some cross-grain'd scurrilous fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that will not be governed by our own grand Jury, but rather contest with his Highness right to <hi>Rowpits,</hi> and bids defiance to prerogative Power, or are back'd by a malitious faction that would hinder the growth of the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacons</hi> Philosophy in recovering the same for the glory of the Nation these considerations, and at our request to him upon the aforesaid agreement that he would shew his quondam Masters Philosophy for recovering <hi>Rowpits</hi> and Green oare from their inundations of water, which is well known to us to be rich in the treasures of Ledd, and to free other works of greater moment from their contagious damps, that now lie deserted, on purpose that the overplus of their revenew, proceeding from such a deplorable condition, and raised by the hand of Providence and Industry, might go (as Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi> did likewise aver, upon the word of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman) to charitable uses of discovering richer Mettals exprest in his late Remonstrance to his Highness, aswell as by his late Will and Testament, for the first fruits thereof to ledd the Tower and Schoole in the Church of <hi>Wells.</hi> Wee of the grand Jury do likewise make this Order and Decree, That if any misdemeanor as aforesaid, shall be proved to be done against the said <hi>Tho. Bushell,</hi> his Agents, Servants, or works, such are not only to be banished the occupation upon <hi>Mendyp,</hi> but wee do humbly implore his Highness to send them to the Mines of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> that they may not infect others, nor bring by their exorbitant corses more scandall upon the whole profession of a Miners innocent calling; since we are satisfied in our consciences, that the way of Mr. <hi>Bushell's</hi> Mineral proceedings, will in this Age bring wonderfull things to pass, and be admired in the next, for the glory of the Nation, And especially when as the said <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> doth aver that he wil transport all his rich Western
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199121:29"/> Mines, lying upon the Sea-side, which are or shall be disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in <hi>Wales, Devon, Cornwall</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> unto the Port or Haven at <hi>Uphill,</hi> to receive their true separations according to the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacons</hi> Philosophy, and so to be minted in the adjacent City of <hi>Wells</hi> for satisfying all returns aswell as to pay the Miner with his own Coyn, and (without any further salary then in one place) to pay the whole of that Commerce.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Jo. Radford</hi> Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Mineral Grand Jury there, with his fellows.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Walter Webb.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Franke.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Adams.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jahn Phelps.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Younge.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Dowling.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Alexandor Cuer.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Hopkins</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jonas Lexstond.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John House.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Ayrer.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199121:29"/>
            <head>A Table setting forth the manner of that great Philosopher the Lord Chancelor <hi>Bacons</hi> searching for Mettals by making Addits through the lowest Level of Hills or Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and conveying Aire into the innermost parts of their Center by Pipe and Bellows; as well as by Art to mollifie the hardest Stone, without the tedious way and inestimable charge of sinking Aery Shafts; and is now intended to be put in practice by his Menial Servant <hi>Thomas Bushel,</hi> on <hi>Hingston-Down,</hi> and other places, according to his Lordships command, and the approbation of that great Mineralist, Sir <hi>Francis Godolphin.</hi>
               <figure/>
            </head>
            <p>FIrst, the true description of <hi>Hingston down,</hi> lieth in Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West</hi> five Miles, with Millions of Shafts that have been visibly Sunk upon several loads of Mettall, by the <hi>Romans, Danes, Saxons, Jews,</hi> and <hi>Britans,</hi> And is in breadth 700 Fathom, at the <hi>Basis</hi> lying <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> as well as in depth 200
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199121:30"/> Fathom from the <hi>Beacon</hi> Perpendicular to the <hi>Center</hi> of that Addit now intended.</p>
            <div type="reason">
               <head>The reason why I undertake a work of this nature, and in these parts, is as followeth;</head>
               <p>FIrst, a gratefull Ambition to answer his Highness Heroick trust re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed in me to discover this Nations Mineral Treasure.</p>
               <p>Secondly, my obliged fidelity to my Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon,</hi> to practice this his Philosophical invention, for the General good; and in particular to give new birth to the drooping conditions of my fellow Pupills, the poor Miners drowned and deserted works.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, my Cordial desire to serve these <hi>Western</hi> parts with the benefit of so usefull a president, I having already practised the same in <hi>Wales</hi> and found the fruitfull effects thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="reasons">
               <head>Secondly, the reasons why I begin my Addit or Aqueducts from Small-Coome and Hooke-Coome, to meet underneath the <hi>Beacon</hi> at the aforesaid <hi>Center, is;</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrst, for that by mine own experience, I found not any of our Predecessors to search lower then 40 Fathom. So that I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently assured that cutting <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South</hi> thorough the aforesaid 700 Fathom, I shall command all the Loads, Rakes, and Veins of Mettal in that Hill; and how probable then it may be to discover ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Indies</hi> out of the drowned and deserted works of our Nation by this example, I shall leave to the rational Judgments of them who are practitioners in those affairs; Especially whether these mine endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors will not give much hopes to verifie the old Proverb, <hi>Hingston-down well wrought, is worth London town dearly bought.</hi> For if the riches of those Groves in 40 Fathom sinking, hath occasioned the aforesaid proverb, as well as the inundation of water hath caused them to desert from their Mineral profit, it cannot be denied by common sense, or rules of reason, this Addit undermining most of the said works 150 Fathom, and then ascending up into their seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral loads of Metal, to drain the waters in their old Groves, but that it carries the fairest encouragement of probable conjecture to make good the true riches of the old proverb of <hi>Hingston down,</hi> in this age of ours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="reason">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:199121:30"/>
               <head>The reason why I use Pipe and Bellows, is,</head>
               <p>FIrst, to convey Aire into the innermost part of my Addit without the sinking of Airy shafts, and preventing the vast expence and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diousness of time, which caused our Forefathers being ignorant of this invention, to leave such supposed riches of hidden Treasure to us their posterity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="reason">
               <head>The reason why I make my Addit or Aqueducts open <hi>150</hi> Fathom at each end, is,</head>
               <p>FIrst, to facilitate the dispatch of 300 Fathom of the 700 the first year, by the reason of the multitude of hands that may be set on work, which will not be admitted if close, and likewise it being the shallowest place of the Hill, it will require but the same expence.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the close Addit may be but in length 400 Fathom of the 700 and to shorten likewise the drift of the same in point of time, I begin my Addits at each end of my open Trench as Counterdrifts to meet each other; And so consequently the whole will be dispatched in half the time; And therefore you may rest assured that I have so maturely calculated the ways and means, not only of this great work at <hi>Hingston-down,</hi> but also of that of <hi>Coom-Martin</hi> in <hi>Devon, Guinop</hi> in <hi>Cornwal,</hi> and <hi>Mendyp</hi> in <hi>Summerset,</hi> that I doubt not, but in four years to set a period to all expectations, if God permit, and I have the honor of your wellwishes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="reason">
               <head>The reason why I do not willingly desire any Partner but Providence, in this great enterprize, is,</head>
               <p>FIrst, because I have had already the experience of some Partners, and found the fruits of Providence to assist me more when they did ever decline the Mineral design, then when I had compliance with their several purses, which made me call to mind his Lordships frequent ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation, that many partners in the publick acts of Mineral adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, where greediness of gain had more rule in their hearts, then to illustrate the Creators glory, became usually the sad <hi>Elogie</hi> of misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and disencouragement to others. Besides, one tenth part must be solely dedicated to prosecute the like works in the other 20 Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains marked out by the aforesaid Lord, and that great Mineralist Sir <hi>Francis Godolphin,</hi> who both subscribed it under their hands, to be the most harmless gain, and greatest good to a Common-wealth, the choicest study and endeavors of the best bred persons in other
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199121:31"/> Nations; and the most Honorable Imployment this world was capable of.</p>
               <p>Lastly, Because I conceive all Mines were created for Mans use, and Gods glory, but in what Age to be revealed, or by whom, is only known to the Searcher of all hearts, who can best judge of mine, and my designed ends.</p>
               <p>And what person then of an ingenuous spirit that is not impoisoned with envie, will bear unfriendly thoughts to those that search after such subterranean treasure at their own charge, for the good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of their native Country, and which in a manner is presented unto them by the hands of God?</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>May it please your Lordships.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE in all humbleness make bold to certifie your Honors, that Mr. <hi>Bushels</hi> way of Mineral proceed to undermine the waters of drowned and deserted Works, is, as we humbly conceive, of such high concernment for the honor and profit of this Nation, as we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently believe before our Lady day next, he will crown his labors with store of hidden Treasure out of the Works now in <hi>Rowpits,</hi> and be inabled, though at present poor in purse, to put on all his other Works of the West; without any Partnership but Providence to assist his Industry, which we find by his daily expression, to be his sole am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of gratitude for his Highness trusting him in that Affair, and in obedience to his old Masters commands the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon,</hi> for the service of his Country in those particulars.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Valent. Trime,</hi> Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of <hi>Chewton</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty wherein <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits</hi> is.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Alexander Jet.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Christ. Wright.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ja. Middleham.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rob. Hill.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Ford.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ralph Conyers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hen. Baron.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Valent. Powel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Nixton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich. Frier</hi> senior.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich Frier</hi> junior.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Hole.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Vigor.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wil. Smith</hi> Mayor.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. White</hi> Recorder</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Salmon</hi> Justice.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Walrond.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Bampfield.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho: Coward.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wil. Morgan</hi> Esquirs.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199121:31"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Mr Bushels PETITION</hi> to the late KING. <hi>TO THE Kings most excellent Majesty.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The humble Petition of <hi>THOMAS BUSHEL</hi> Your Majesties Servant,</head>
            <opener>Most humbly sheweth,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT whereas your Royal Father of ever blessed memory, who was truly stiled the King of Peace, and mirror of mercy to the sparing of life and bloud, was graciously pleased, for saving the lives of such malefactors as were condemned to death by the Law for petty fellonies, being such as were not any scandal to the Church or State, not had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewed their hands in bloud, to admit their transportation to the <hi>East-India</hi> and <hi>Virginia</hi> Companies, for furtherance of their plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. In which action, doubtless, he did also cast his eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the warrantable proceedings and presidents of other most fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Princes in the like kind, as the late Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who built certain Gallies of purpose for imployment of such kind of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, of strong and able bodies, as might attend her memorable designs at Sea, especially upon all sudden and resolute enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes, it being the usual course of other Christian Princes, as the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> both for the supply of his Gallies against the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Moores,</hi> and especially for the inlargement of his <hi>Indian</hi> Mines of Gold, Silver, Quicksilver, and the like, and his conquests of <hi>Molocco, Goa, Ormus,</hi> and other rich and populous Ilands. The King of <hi>France</hi> for his Gallies at <hi>Marsellis.</hi> The State of <hi>Venice.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> who by such kind of saved Offenders built
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199121:32"/>
               <hi>Ligorn</hi> (one of the most famous Sea-ports within the <hi>Straits.</hi>) In all which States and Services, divers of these malefactors, by good incouragements have sought, not so much by surviving, as by their incredible labours, effecting matters otherwise held in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible, to obliterate their former ignominies by merit of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. And whereas in this your Majesties populous Kingdom, too many such offenders are most untimely cut off in their best abilities of service, so is there within the pale of this Your Kingdom, and without any occasion of Sea, or forein service, means of imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for such persons, to redeem their lost reputation, by indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to doe faithfull service for their Countries honour, and the Kingdoms good, in that happy work, begun by Your Sacred Majesty, for the better discovery of Your Silver Mines. His most humble sute therefore is, that you would be pleased out of all these weighty considerations and beneficial consequences, tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so much to your Honor, Crown and Dignity, and good of the Common-wealth, to grant Your Majesties commission, (if it may be thought fit by the advice of Your High and Honourable Court of Parliament) for the choosing of such several persons out of the prisons of this your Kingdome, as are, and shall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for small offences, and of able serviceable bodies, by the approbation of Your Judges, and shall implore Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties mercy, to be imployed by your said Subject in the Works of your Mines-Royal, they giving security for their good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, with such limitation of time, and allowance for their sustentation, as to Your Majesties said High Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment shall be thought fit, that by their dutifull and laborious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance therein, they may afterwards come into the happinesse of your Majesties pardon of Grace for their former offence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And your Petitioner shall ever rest, &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>The Speech of the late Bishop of <hi>Worcester</hi> (near his death) to Mr. <hi>Bushell,</hi> concerning the two rich Mines by him discovered.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. Bushell,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur own eyes see how near I am to the dwelling of death, by my gray hairs which are the true Records of fourscore and fourteen years of age, next my limbs which have no more
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199121:32"/> strength, than those that are lap'd in the Sepulchre of their winding sheet, only my intellectual parts are yet preserved, to ascribe God the glory, and to disclose the secrets of two rich Mines, the one holding some quantity of Gold worth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting, the other in Silver worth the Refining; to your trust and fidelity, with a confidence that your charity cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me guilty, of betraying your judgement with an imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry treasure, when my Soul and Body are so near the approach of death, as I must suddainly give an account in the other World; besides, I have taken upon me, the calling of a spiritual professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and have this day received the Sacrament, as a pledge of my redemption, which I trust are sufficient motives, to believe truth from a dying mans tongue, who hath no other end, than that the hopefulnesse of such riches, may not be buried by my dissolution, but that the honour and profit thereof might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>downd to his <hi>Majesty,</hi> and his royal posterity, as a living and loyal remembrance of his Princely favours to tree and mine.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To our Dread Soveraign Lord the KINGS most Excellent MAJESTY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it please your Majesty,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVEE doe most humbly and thankfully acknowledge, that your Majesties vouchsafing to this your Principality the trust of a branch of your Royal Mint, is an honour that neither our Ancestors nor our selves durst wish for; and we do as hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and as thankfully acknowledge and confesse, that by it you have not only honoured us more, than any of your Royal prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors; but have thereby offered us the means to enrich our selves, to the making of us happier than our fathers, in freeing us from the cares and fears that hindred us from diving into these Mountains that promise a masse of treasure. For be pleased to know, that before your Majesty vouchsafed unto us this great favour, we were fearful to adventure far into the mountains, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we had far to send before we could make the silver current, that we should at charge recover. Nor was our care of carriage and recarriage the least hinderance to our proceedings, from all which, by your Majesties goodnesse, and the endeavours of your industrious and faithful servant <hi>Thomas Bushel,</hi> we are happily
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199121:33"/> freed; for which favour, we whose names are hereunto subscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the behalfe of all the inhabitants of this your Principality of WALES, doe render all humble and hearty thanks, and for them, and our selves, doe hereby promise to Your sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, that we will doe our utmost endeavours, to finde out that measure, which wee be leeve God and Nature from the Creation hath preserved for your Majestyes use; that thereby we may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove our selves your Majesties loyal and most obedient Subjects, and humble Servants.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Milward</hi> Knight,</item>
                     <item>Chiefe Iustice of <hi>Chester.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Marmaduke LLoyd</hi> Knight.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Price</hi> K. Baronet.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iames Price</hi> Knight.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sampson Eure</hi> Knight.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Lewis</hi> Knight.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Timothy Turner</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>L. Littleton</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Walter LLoyd</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Price</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Corbet</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Evan Gwin</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Morgan Herbert</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Vaughan</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vincent Corbet</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Humfrey Greene</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn LLoyd</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>David LLoyd ap Reigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nald</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Phillips</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Edmund</hi> Esq;</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hugh LLoyd</hi> Gentlem.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>David Rees</hi> Gent.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Bowen</hi> Gent.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Watkin</hi> Gent.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Meredith</hi> Gent.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iames Kegitt</hi> Gent.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Certificate from the <hi>Miners</hi> presented to the Right Honourable, the Lords and other of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties most Honourable Privy Councel.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it please your Lordships,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ACcording to your commands, Wee whose names are under written, being <hi>Miners, Smelters, Refiners, Carryers, Washers,</hi> an <hi>Monyers</hi> belonging to his Majesties <hi>Mines Royal,</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Cardigan,</hi> in all humility do certifie of our certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and experience, concerning the new works lately discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Gods providence to <hi>Thomas Bushell</hi> Esquire, Farmer of his Majesties <hi>Mines-Royal</hi> in these parts, that the said Master <hi>Bushell</hi> at his inestimable charge, having cut six hundred Fathome through the Rock at the lowest levels, North and South, for dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the lost veine of <hi>Cum-sum</hi> lock, lying East and West,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199121:33"/> two hundred Fathome through the Mountain of <hi>Tallibont</hi> at sixty Fathome perpendicular, three several <hi>Addits</hi> at <hi>Koginenn,</hi> one above another twenty and thirty Fathome center, another at the <hi>Darren,</hi> to come under the <hi>Romans</hi> work, at an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Fathom center, another at <hi>Bryn Lloyd</hi> fifty Fathom in length, and thirty Fathom center, working day and night for the Drayning of the water, which formerly in the time of Customer <hi>Smith,</hi> and Sir <hi>Hugh Middleton</hi> in their working of the <hi>Mines Royall</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver used, they only working upon the Superficies of the Earth, the works being drowned with water before they could sink to the best of the vein, both for quantity and quality, and so the charge made to exceed the benefit, which danger is prevented by the aforesaid <hi>Addits,</hi> and the <hi>Royall Mines</hi> become more hopeful, especially by the assistance of his Majesties Mint, for the speedy payment of all those that are imployed in the said works, and Mr. <hi>Bushels</hi> own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention to save Wood, by reducing the Ore into Lead, and Silver, with Turffe and Sea-cole Charked, which happy invention, had it not been found out, the works must needs have been left unwrought, the Country not able to have supplied necessary fewell. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by the prohibition of transporting Ore unwrought, that hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth silver worth the refining, which His <hi>Majesty</hi> in his Princely wisdom saw to be very prejudicial, even to the utter overthrow of his <hi>Mines-Royall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have therefore great reason to be confident that his way of Working, with the restraint of transporting Ore, will in short time greatly increase the Bullion of this Kingdom, for the honour of the King, and good of the Common-wealth, together with the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of many hundred poor people, which would be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise an unsupportable burthen to this barren Country, who by rheir present labour in these <hi>Mines</hi> are able to subsist with their Family, and thousands more might be daily set on work if Mr. <hi>Bushels</hi> undertakings in the <hi>Mines-Royall</hi> may be confirmed for a certain time by this present High Court of Parliament.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <head>Miners.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>David Fowles.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Rashly.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henry Cockler.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>David Bebb.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioseph Iefferies.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Turner.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Lowning.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Fletcher.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>David Evans.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Dixon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hugh Mason.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>David ap Richard.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>David Loyd.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>David Williams,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henry Emblin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Maurice Taylor.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Emblin,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward Reece.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:199121:34"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hugh Reece.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Davids.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Scotsmer.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Brickhead.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Griffith.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter Baltiser.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Francis Pierce.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Maurice Lewis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter Edriser.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward Blewys.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rob. Emblin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rob. Tailor.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>David Iinkins.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioseph Acherson.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Blewys.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Michael Sanders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Morgan Williams.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Clocker.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Greene.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Barthol. Clocker.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Francis Fisher.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hugh Benn.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Mason.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Tickle.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Mason.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Fisher.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edmund Poole.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edw. Bebb.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Mason</hi> sen.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Ficharets.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Evan Thomas.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Harris.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Tyson.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Watkin Reece.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Smith.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Morgan Pritchet.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Griffith Iohn.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Reece.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Tuddar.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Huson.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Philip Benn.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Iames.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>With two Hundred more, whom for brevity we omit to name.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <head>Moniers.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Henry Such.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iohn Corbet.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Richard Arnold.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Refiners.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iohn Estopp.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>David Estopp.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Samuel Iohnson.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edw. Gibbon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Parker.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Arthur Elissa.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Smelters.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Botham.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hugh Iames.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Griffith Evans.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iohn Watkin.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iinkin Owen.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iohn Epslie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iohn Evans.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iohn Lewes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iames Meredith.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Washers.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iohn Wringe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Morgan Iohn Lewis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Davy Iohn.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iohn Iinkins.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Morgan Griff. Iohn.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edmund Symons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Reece Morgan.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Charles Williams.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Adams;</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To the Right Honourable the <hi>Lords</hi> and others of his <hi>Majesties</hi> most Honourable <hi>Privy Councill.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ACcording to Your Honours command we have enquired and considered how the <hi>Mines-Royal</hi> were left to Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi> by the Lady <hi>Middleton,</hi> and do in all humility declare, that the silver Mines were not worth the working, untill Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi> at his great charge discovered Rich Ore in the adjacent mountains, which in all likelihood will both increase the Bullion, and by his way of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199121:34"/> in short time give his Majesty a true tryal what the invaluable riches of these His <hi>Welsh</hi> mountains are: for whereas the Mines in these parts were formerly wrought by Pumps, and so growing deep were left drowned with water; Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi> cuts through the main Rocks, at the lowest levell, to an hundred farhom perpendicular, according to the German manner of working, which though chargeable, yet certain, having four several Addits which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth driving day and night into four several mountains; his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry also hath outstript former times, for by melting the poor fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fible Ore, with the Rich, he produceth a third part more of silver with the same charge: and for accommodating the works with all materials fit for <hi>Mines-Royal,</hi> he hath spared no cost about repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the mils, hath also built in his Majesties Castle of <hi>Aberystwith</hi> a fair Mint, hath contracted with Merchants of our own and other Nations to supply the p oples necessity with Corn and other provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, and payeth the Miners and carriers at the Scales, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to make them able Pyoners, and fit Souldiers to do his Majesty and their Country service upon any assault of an enemy. All which we commend to your Honourable consideration, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordships humbly to be commanded</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioseph Hexsteter,</hi> chief Steward of the Mines</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Samuel Reynish,</hi> Assay Masters of the Mint.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Water Barkesby,</hi> Assay Masters of the Mint.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Humphrey Owen,</hi> Clark of the Mines.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Die Sabbati <hi>14.</hi> Aug. <hi>1641.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHereas this House hath been informed, that <hi>Thomas Bushell</hi> Esquire, undertaker of his Majesties Mines-Royal in the County of <hi>Cardigan,</hi> by his great charge and industry in cutting Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits hath gained His Majesties old drowned and forsaken works of <hi>Tallybont,</hi> and other works, And made new discoveries of Royal Mines there, which are already very considerable; And whereas di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers persons of quality encouraged by his Majesties Letters to them directed, do intend to adventure great sums of money in the said works, which in time (if well incouraged) may prove of great conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, both for Honour and Profit to His Majesty and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199121:35"/> And whereas also it appeareth unto this House by divers Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davits and Certificats of credit that some persons ill affected to these Honourable and Publick services who in time may receive deserved punishments, have disturbed the possession of the said <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> in some of His Majesties Mines-Royal, and Edifices appertaining to the Royal-works, and have plucked up divers plumps cast in the Rubbish, drowned, and (so much as in them did lye) destroyed the said works, so as it hath been a labour of four years night and day to recover the same. And that also the said <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> hath been di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbed in the getting of Turfe and Peat for the Service of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties works, being an invention of his own, very commendable and commodious for the preserving of wood, which hath been hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the former undertakers much wasted in those parts. Now for the remedy of the said mischiefs, and that the said <hi>Tho. Bushhll</hi> and his assigns, and such persons as are or shall be Undertakers and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers with him in the said service may receive all due incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Assistance in those chargeable undertakings; It is ordered by the Lords in the upper House of <hi>Parliament</hi> now assembled, That the <hi>Speaker</hi> of this House, in the Name, and by the Authority of the same, shall direct His Letters unto the Judges of Assize, and Justices of the Peace of the said County of <hi>Cardigan:</hi> Requiring them, that they do in all law ul things endeavour to advance, and encourage the said sereice in his Majesties Royal Mines, and assist the said <hi>Tho. Bush ll</hi> and other Undertakers, in all things so far as lawfully they may, both for the continuance of his lawful Possessions, and the quiet and peaceable working of the said mines, untill he shall be evicted by due course of Law, as also for getting and working of Turfe and Peat, according to his Legal right upon his Majesties Wastes, and other places lawful, and all other lawful accommodations of necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry passages, and other Legal things, which may any wayes advance His Majesties service in the said Royal Mines.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JO. BROWNE <hi>Cler. Parliament.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter from the L. Keeper, to the Justices of Assize, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>AFter my very hearty Commendations, I have here inclosed sent you an Order made in the House of the <hi>Lords</hi> now assembled in <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> which you are carefully to observe and perform according to the directions thereof in all things, so far as Lawfully you may. So not doubting of your readiness therein, I bid you heartily farewell and rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your very loving friend</hi> Ed. Littleton <hi>Cust. Sig.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Excester-house,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>26. Aug. 1641</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199121:35"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Bushell's</hi> Invitation by Letter to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned men for Petty-felonies, to work in the Mines of their own Country, rather then be banish'd to Slavery in Foreign parts.</head>
            <p>FEllow-sufferers in restraint, although upon different ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, for you have sought death by the errors of your lives, I an Imprisonment by a licentious Prodigalitie; But I hope your Consciences (like faithful Mirrors) have presented to the eye of your afflicted souls the deformities of your several Crimes, as mine hath to my serious considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion my manifold Transgressions: We have no City of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge in these our sad perplexities; the impartial doom of our Laws hath banished you from the land of the living, unless its mercy exile you from the land of your nativitie by a ten years absence to a sordid slaverie in some torrid Island, whose climate, air, diet, and manner of labor will prove very irksom unto you; But the implacable revenge of some of my Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors doth endeavor to burie me alive in this house of woe, when (God knows) I was plung'd in my Mineral inundations with care and pains to pay them their just debts by the help of Providence.</p>
            <p>But, dear Brethren, Friends, and Companions in Bonds, to assure you that I commiserate your deplorable condition more then mine own, I would present you with a more so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacious Cordial then that of societie in your miseries, which I have humbly petitioned the honorable Parliament for, and hope I shall obtain to your temporal and eternal advantage. You are therefore first to understand, that when our English <hi>Aristotle,</hi> Natures best modern Secretary, that excellent Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199121:36"/> the Lord Chancellor <hi>BACON,</hi> my ever honored Master, had compleated his now extant Natural History of Philosophical Experiments, he then modell'd his <hi>Solomon's House</hi> in his <hi>New Atlantis</hi> thereto annexed, in which Academy they might be practised; but not by those common waies (as he was used to say) where even Fools might raise a <hi>Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, Colossus,</hi> or <hi>Mausoleum</hi> to their ridiculous memories, <hi>Viz.</hi> from the Exchequers of bounteous and magnificent Princes, Piratick depredations, or Monopolous exactions from an opulent people; but rather by a Philosophical E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixar and Chymical extraction, so quaint and admirable, that it seems to convince the Maxim, <hi>Out of nothing is made, nothing.</hi> For he proposed no other means to erect and maintain that stupendious Fabrick and the <hi>Magi</hi> thereof, who were by him designed thereto by his Theorie, then the recoverie of the Lost by the help of the Dead. Resolve the Riddle, and find your Cordial; for though it be truly Magical, 'tis not Necro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantick.</p>
            <p>But not to delay you, I (as your <hi>Oedipus</hi>) thus open it: The <hi>Lost,</hi> are drowned and desperately deserted Mineral Works; the <hi>Dead,</hi> convicted and attainted persons, who are indeed so in Law; and what is lost, is not in nature as to the use and proprietie of mankind. Cheer up my Comrades, I have opened my dark lantern to you, and light is comfortable to the benighted. Now know, that that excellent Lord af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting my homebred simplicitie, and being ambitious to raise a Younger brothers fortunes by such Experiments, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted me as his much favored Pupil in his misterious Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophical way of recovering and searching Mines, by molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying their hardest Rocks, undermining their Waters, sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating their Metals, and carrying Air through their lowest levels of hills or mountains, without the vastness of former charge to sink Shafts for air every twenty fathom. But he suddenly falling from an eminent heigth, as I by that time had deviated from his grave directions in the secure paths of Vertue, imposed on me a new task, which was not to search
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199121:36"/> the rockie bosoms of the barren Mountains, but by a timely retirement to some solitarie place where I might seclude my self from the treacherous vanities of the tumultuous world, to explore the deceitful meanders of my stonie Heart, and when Divine grace should have assisted my better Reason in over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the rebellious affections of my sensual appetite, if then the like providence should call me thence to a more active life in the prosecution of his Mineral documents, I should without any regret of my former penance attend the good hand of God in that design with humble patience; as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suredly believing, that since he had supported me in the conquest of my self, he would conduct me through all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, to the accomplishing so great a work for my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries good, and his own glory. And according to his counsel and prediction, after I had lived three years as a Recluse in a desolate Island in the Irish seas, only conversing with God in my repentant tears, prayers and contemplations, he mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culously called me thence to an unexpected fortune, brought me into favor with my Prince, who granted me a Patent for all the Mines-Royal, in order to my Lords Proposals, and a Branch of his Royal Mint to coin such Silver as I should extract from all Lead of my own finding; which was not a little, witness the many great services I did for that King therewith, notwithstanding my great losses in the late Wars. But as the Times, so we in them are chang'd.</p>
            <p>Now here to prevent any that may ask, why since by my Articles of War I am to be restored to all my former rights, I seek no more from the present State, then an assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the deserted Mines of our Territories? I answer, that they will be enough, which is better then more: that then I was no way obnoxious to that government but in my Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes favor, and he in Peace, now these States look upon me as a pardoned and reconciled Enemy; and their vast ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence in the Republick service, permits Delinquents no such allowance, therefore I modestly ask the crumbs which they scorne to gather up, and therewith doubt not to performe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199121:37"/> my undertakings to the honor of my Country, and my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters memory. But me thinks I heare our proud first Enemy (that envious spirit of delusion) whisper to some of you, What will your condition of slavery be better here in your native Mines, then in a forreign Plantation, where your friends cannot see your sufferings, nor you their prosperities, to their or your afflictions, because they cannot mitigate yours, nor you participate of theirs, which will be no small abatement to your shames, and their sorrows? To this I reply, that as the innocence of the sufferer, not the rigor of the torment makes one a Martyr, so the cause of shame is in the act of the Crime, not in the nature of the servitude; wheresoever to be suffered, your guilt is known, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies you every where; is it not then better here to expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate it where a safer and easier meanes is offered, if you intend to lead a new life? Consider the tediousnes and dangers of your transportations, through Stormes, Enemies, and a sparing salt diet: If you Land safely, 'tis but to be sold like Beasts, and most likely to men of barbarous soules, through whose cruelty you shall gasp out your dolorous lives with excessive labors; and when Hunger shall call for natures recruits, be forced to think the worst imployed horses of your own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try happier then your selves in their natural food; and after all this, if you can outlive your bondage in inriching your taskmasters, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> for revenge or avarice may surprize your completed plantations, and carry you away to consume the sad remnant of your miserable dayes in his Mines, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out merit, expiation, or hope; but thus you cannot suffer at home, where you may turne your necessities into vertues, by a patient and humble submission to Gods will, for all evill of punishment is from him. I propose not this to you as Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Pionears out of any design of advantage to my self, your food, clothes, and materials, wil cost me as much as the hired expert Miners, my plot upon you is the only salvation of your soules, and restitution of your liberties, through your contrition and penance by Christs merits and Gods mercy,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199121:37"/> with temporal rewards of benefit, and expiation by your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious discoveries in your allotted portions; which that you may obtain, sacrifice but your sins on the broken altars of your contrite hearts to the Lord of mercies, and you have his own word for your free pardons. O how will your conversion and deliverance make your friends and the Angels of Heaven to rejoyce, for I verily believe the true compunction of your hearts will more facilitate the penetration of our Rockie Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits then the strokes of your hands: And to incourage and assist you therein, I shall provide such holy and Orthodox Instructors for you, that by your conscientious observance of their moral and divine lectures as well as their examples, you shall with much alacrity be able to overcome all the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacles of this great work; for they will voluntarily participate with you in all things, that thereby they may cheerfully lead you into Christs own fould. And therefore consult with your consciences &amp; they wil doubtless dictate to your memories, that the best way to pilot your sad souls, bodies, lives, and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from tempestuous stormes of worldly vanities into a safe harbor, was with humble hearts to take this Mineral calling upon you, and to think, speak, and deport your selves towards God in it, as if all the world did behold you, and to live and converse with man as in the immediate sight of our divine Creator, and then we shall rejoyce in enjoying one another; for as I desire the Almighty, not to forgive me my sins, nor receive my soul, if I have any other ends then what hath bin exprest, so I desire none of you to remove your selves to this harmless and laborious calling, unless your reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions be firm to those ends, which may crown your industry, otherwise we must be forc'd in obedience to our trust, to return you back to the Judge of your first condemnation, and pray that the All disposer may call you by some other means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, which shall be the constant and fervent petition of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your most Compassionate Friend</hi> Thomas Bushell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:199121:38"/>
            <head>To my Fellow-Prisoners for Debt, in Mind or Body.</head>
            <p>DEarly beloved Brethren in bonds, I could heartily rejoice if we were so only for Christs sake, for then our patience therein would render us happy in his mercy: Yet since the inhumanity of our Creditors (through the power of the Laws) usurps that revenge which is only God's in justice, let us with all humility submit our selves to his permissive will, for the evil of punishment is his. My honorable Master the late Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon</hi> was wont to tell me, That as Gentry bought nothing at Market, so Imprisonment paid no Debts, but those of the Penal laws; and that he did verily believe, the fradulent Contracts of most Creditors begot the disability of their Debtors satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. I shall refer to your own consciences the respective cause of your several restraints: Mine own is like that of the adventurous Merchant, who having sent all his own Stock in several Vessels to far distant Factories through the various dangers of the Deep, is constrained to take up on Trust at home, till the return of his Cargazoons according to their success proclaim him happy, or bankrupt; and if I had ever any other design in borrowing, let my Redeemer exclude me from the general pardon of his precious merits, who came not to call the just, but sinners to repentance, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suring us that the blessed Angels rejoice more at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of one true Penitent, then the integrity of ninety nine righteous; from whence we may conclude, 'tis ninety nine to one odds, that there are very few sincere Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts.</p>
            <p>But my beloved Fellow-sufferers, since now the Supreme Power of this Commonwealth doth, as I hear, intend like S. <hi>Peters</hi> good Angel to open the doors of your Prisons by the wisdom of their mercies, I earnestly exhort you to mark
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199121:38"/> the first day of your unexpected Jubile with a white stone or red letter, in commemoration of so happy a deliverance, (lest God consume your lives with new afflictions &amp; troubles) alwaies remembring his glory and your own eternity: And then take the grave admonition for your Cure, as the Mirror of my honored Master prescribed to me, which was, To deny all my treacherous Senses their most delighting Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: I fed on nothing that pleased my appetite; looking willingly on nothing which I formerly liked; nor accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied any creature that affected my concupiscence; But frequented devious waies and solitary groves, and at last found out a desolate Island in the Irish seas, where three years I sadly lamented the errors of my youth, mingling the waters which I drank with the brine of mine eies, and did sparingly eat the bread of affliction as it had been ashes. These were my first steps towards Gods Mercy-seat, in a most unfained contrition for the Treason I committed against his Eternal Majesty: And surely he was not displeased therewith; for out of this depth of desolation he graciously called me to the publique service of my Country, in the innocent way of a Miner; and how I have proceeded therein, with inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion chiefly to glorifie him, this annexed Treatise will give you an account. But there the inhumanity of my Creditors stopt me; yet I am confident, so soon as the Republique-affairs will permit, the Honorable Parliament will enlarge me in order to my Mineral service, and their own Articles, as they have done you in mercy: And then I say, if any of you (either for a present subsistence, or a penitential way to expiate your former errors, or to reclaim your affections, or in hope to raise your lost fortunes and enable you to pay your honest Debts) will sweat with me in the way of this hopeful, vertuous, and Philosophical labor, you shall eat bread with me so long as you please, whereby at last we may obtain such Mineral blessings from the Lord of Bounty, that we in true charity may be able to eat our bread upon the waters, by relieving many distressed Penitents whose
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199121:39"/> sins have brought them to want bread, and whose age or sickness hath taken away their ability to work.</p>
            <p>And here I think 'tis proper to give you the Epitome of my Lords Design for the regulating his <hi>Solomon's House</hi> or <hi>Academy.</hi> He proposes six principal Officers of State to succeeding times as Trustees, six exquisite lucre-hating Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers to bring his Theorie into experimental practice, are to be handsomly maintained, upon a sacred oath to be true to the trust of his Philosophical secrets; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed men and adventurous Voluntiers, are to be chief instruments of the Mineral work, and are to be clothed in good Canvas or Welsh Cottons, their food Bisket, Beef, Pease and Bacon thrice a week, the other daies White-meat, Oil and Roots; their drink of allowance for the most part is to be Water, but they shall not be barr'd Beer or Ale in orderly proportion; they are to lie on Mats, unless they rather choose a clean Plank; Lots and Delves shall be assigned to them, in which if God bless their honest diligence, they shall comfortably participate, whereby at last they may make themselves free, if a true and constant penitence be their heavenly guide; for impenitence barra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadoes the gates of heaven faster rgainst us then our sins: For as true contrition makes our hearts grateful sacrifices to God, so earnest prayer on her dove-like wings presents them before his Mercies seat, and unfained penitence softly sheaths up the sword of his Justice. And for your better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, if you come cheerfully into this Philosophical work, you shall also enter into the school of Christ; for I shall provide men excellently qualified in Theology, Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Humanity, whose examples as well as doctrines shall direct you in the waies of eternal life, and daily walk hand in hand with you towards Christs paradise, the Saints New Jerusalem.</p>
            <p>But methinks I heare some self conceited and censorious Critick thus prevaricate upon the whole design: Truly I must profess it seems to my understanding very like a lunacie
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199121:39"/> in any whatsoever to propose or undertake so magnificent a Fabrick as the <hi>Atlantick Solomons house,</hi> without so much as Straw to burn, Bricks for its foundation, no Princes Coffers, Monopoly, Smoke-mony, Lottery, Impost or Mart upon the discovery, but to the incredulous, no not so much as a partner save Providence in this new way of search for never discovered Mines, and recovering desperately deserted Works. To which I answer, first if your Ancestors in former ages had been such Scepticks, fire had been for ever concealed in the Flint, and all Metals in their native beds, <hi>Thule</hi> with the Western Islands and <hi>America</hi> had been as yet undiscovered: pray tell me, is not Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence the dispensator of Gods Omnipotence? which the Eagle-sighted eye of this Philosophical Lords illuminated intellect most perspicuously discovered, and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved thus to prove it without detriment or hazard to any individuall person: Is it not then a Godlike Imitation? the Lord of the universal World brought all things which never had being, out of nothing; this Lord of universal Philosophy thereby offers mankind that good which never can be usefull to him but by this means, which will cost him nothing, the dead in Law to search the dead and barren Mountains, and recover the dead and buried works; for Mineral treasure here is nothing but the dead, and the dead are nothing to the living. But these dead here (to whose lives the Law and opinion hath set a period) by searching the graves of Minerals, preserve their lives for the present, and in time find their own resurrection by a temporal expiation of their fatall Crimes, though their other hopes prove frustrate: but if the Almighty crowns their labors, observe how glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious it will prove: the Prince or State that shall then Rule, shall receive the first fruits; thousands of poor Subjects shall eat the bread of comfort thereby; Offenders shall be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and freed; Trade shall be increased, and Customs aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, a matchless Academy erected and maintained, new Arts discovered for the universal good, and honor of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199121:40"/> the honorable Trustees of the whole work shall merit glory, and gain philosophical recreations; the experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Philosophers shall have a competent and comfortable subsistence during life, and after their change their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective Statues erected in the City of <hi>Wells;</hi> and as the <hi>Athenians</hi> when they dedicated a lively Image to the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the antient Philosopher <hi>Pherecydes,</hi> gave it a golden tongue, as a proper emblem of his excellent eloquence, so each of theirs shall hold a significant character of their pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Inventions in their well-proportion'd hands. Which word <hi>hands,</hi> minds me of a saying of my Lords concerning the Convicted, which was, That he did stedfastly beleeve that the hands of such whose stony hearts God had penetrated by true penitence, would make a more speedy, easie and successfull progress in any Mineral work they undertook, then three times the number of the most skilful Miners that work for wages only. For that learned Lord was of opinion, that the subterranean Spirits did much hinder the perfect discoveries of the richest Mines, sometimes by their appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition, and often by the mischievous gambols they plaid there, as by raising Damps, extinguishing the Miners lights, firing the sulphurous matter of the Mine, and scorching the greedy and faithless Workmen. For not only <hi>Socrates, Plato,</hi> and <hi>Aristotle</hi> are of opinion, that there are multitudes of Evil Spirits in the Aery region, as also in the Waters, and the hollow Concaverns of the Earth; but divers of our more modern learned Writers and Theologians are of the same perswasion, as <hi>Tho. Aquinas, Gaudentius Merula, Pselius Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinus,</hi> and S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> who conceive that God hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted their temporal habitations therein, partly for mens trial, as that of <hi>Job,</hi> and partly for the punishment of the wicked, as the Demoniack in the 5. of S. <hi>Marks</hi> Gospel, out of whom Christ cast a whole legion of Devils, and by whose permission they destroyed a numerous Herd of the <hi>Gadarens</hi> Swine. These were created in the beginning, as Divines conclude out of the 38. of <hi>Job,</hi> when the <hi>Morning-stars
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199121:40"/> sang together, and all the sons of God shouted for joy;</hi> as may be conjectured at the Archangel <hi>Michaels</hi> victory over <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer</hi> and his rebellious Army of ambitious Spirits: And Christ himself tells us in the 10. of <hi>Luke,</hi> He beheld Satan as Lightning fall from Heaven. What need I say more? That audacious Spirit who had the impudence to tempt our Saviour, daies continually circle the Earth, still like a roaring Lion seeking whom he may devour. But Faith is the best armor, and fervent Prayer the sharpest sword to vanquish him, who being but so resisted flies from us, and true Contrition and humble penance conjures him away: And I pray you who ought to be more cordially penitent, then such whom the just Laws and their own consciences having cast into the jaws of death, Gods mercy hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieved to expiate their crimes in so innocent and hopeful a work as this, to the good of their afflicted souls, their Countries profit, and his own glory? for Penitence, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and vertuous Emulation, are the most prevalent Engines to effect this noble Enterprise; which I had rathet decline and utterly relinquish, then use any corrosive or compulsory means to constrain any of my penitential brethren to proceed in or accelerate their labors, as the <hi>Spaniard</hi> doth to his miserable Miners in <hi>America,</hi> and others in other places.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the validity and grandure of this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterious Attempt, you are to understand that the Colledge of our most honored Physitians, which is the Philosophical Oracle of our Commonwealth, have candidly certified the late Lord Protector <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> That as the Design was heroick and magnificent, so if it were not prejudiced and obstructed by the obloquy and sinister contrivance of self-interessed persons, it was like to produce much profit and honor to this our native Country.</p>
            <p>In a word, howsoever you value my Invitation to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate in my Mineral profession, neglect not my cordial Counsel in matters of Devotion and sincere Penitence:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199121:41"/> For 'tis conceived by some truly religious and very learned, that the Penitent only shall recruit the Regiments and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Host of the intellectual Angels, by supplying the place of them that fell with <hi>Lucifer</hi> in his great Rebellion. To which God of his mercy for the Son of his love's sake bring us all in his appointed time, by what several ends he shall think most fit, is the prayers of your faithfull Friend; as well as to find out by his holy Spirit those freeborn Mines of Noble Souls in either sex for my Executors, as will make the World their Heir, and are endowed with such vertuous Actions of love and charity, as might eternize the memory of my old Master, and magnifie the Creators glory in his works of Nature; which is and shall be the ambition of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your most humble Servant,</hi> Tho. Bushell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:199121:41"/>
            <head>The late Kings Letter of Invitation to Mr. <hi>Bushell,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming his procedure in Mineral discoveries.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>CHARLES R.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>TRusty and welbeloved, We having taken into consideration your late Relation concerning your proceedings and intentions for the perfecting of that great work happily by you begun in Our County of <hi>Cardigan</hi> in Our Principality of <hi>Wales,</hi> concerning those hopeful Mines by you discovered, approving well of your beginnings, proceedings, and intentions, We have thought good out of Our Royal disposition, to the encouraging of you and all such as are studious or industrious, to do to Us or Our Commonwealth profitable service, to assure you by these Our Letters, that you shall not only by Our protection peaceably enjoy the Contract and bargain by you made with the Lady <hi>Elizabeth Middleton</hi> concerning the said Mines, with all things thereunto belonging; but also be well assured, that both you, your Agents, Assistants or Coadjutors, shall from time to time have all the furtherance and favor We can vouchsafe to you or them. And for the better encouraging of you to go cheerfully and confidently on with the works, when your learned Council at the Law shall advise you to pray any further Act or Acts from Us, whereby the designe may be advanc'd, and you and your Assistants secured, you shall find Us ready to grant unto you any your lawful desires: And in the mean time these Our Letters shall be a good and sufficient testimony of Our Royal intentions towards you, and our good wishes to the prosperity of your undertakings. Given at Our Court at <hi>Whitehall</hi> under Our Signet, the three and twentieth day of <hi>February,</hi> in the twelfth year of Our Reign.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>To Our trusty and welbeloved Subject and Servant</hi> Thomas Bushell <hi>Esq;</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>This is entred in the Signet-book</hi>
                  <date>23 <hi>Febr.</hi> 1636. Ja. Store.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Merchants Letter of <hi>Barnstaple</hi> to Mr. <hi>Bushell</hi> concerning their accommodation of transporting his Lead and Oar gratis, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce you have been pleased at your own great charge to discover those deserted Works at <hi>Combmartin</hi> for the publick good of our Country; and whereas you are interessed in the Mines of <hi>Wales</hi> which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199121:42"/> furnish you both with Lead and Lead-Oar. These are to request you, to bedleased to make this our Harbour partaker of the Benefits may proceed therein, and what we buy not from you for ready moneys, we shall be ready to transport for you Frait-free instead of Ballast, you rendring it aboard to all such Ports as our Vessels shall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce withall In so doing, we suppose the result thereof will more properly conduce to your hopefull proceedings in the said works of <hi>Combmartin,</hi> which we wish all happy success, and remain</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Barnstable</hi>
                  <date>6 Octob. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Loving Friends,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Harris</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Leigh.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Shu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>bert Dennis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Tucker.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Horwood.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Anthony Benny,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Palmer.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lyonel Becher.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Harris.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Nottel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Down.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Walter Tucker.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>R. Flemming.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Medford.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Wood.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Francis Newton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward Flemming.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Cox.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nathaniel Fishe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>leigh.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Frayn.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To the Honorable <hi>William Lenthal</hi> Esq; Speaker of the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable house of Commons.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. Speaker,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Formerly granted safe conduct unto <hi>Thomas Bushel</hi> Esq; who had the command of the Isle of <hi>Lundy</hi> to come hither to Treat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the surrender of that place, and he like a Gentleman truly performed on his part such Articles as were agreed on; since which time he hath been very industrious in finding out of Lead Mines, which are like to produce good quantities of Silver, proof whereof you may please to see, and having seen a Letter under the hands of the Merchants of <hi>Barnstable</hi> to further his endeavors for the publick; I could not but out of a sence I have the general good will be exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly advantaged by the way of his industry, humbly offer it as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of mine, That Mr. <hi>Bushel</hi> may have for his better incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, your best assistance in restoring him to all his Estate, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to mine agreement, and the Order of both houses, dated the Tenth of <hi>July,</hi> 1647. And although by that agreement and Order, he humbly conceivs he may justly claim the Customs of Lead of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> at such Rent as the same were formerly granted him by Letters Pattents from his Majesty under the great Seal, for a good
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199121:42"/> Term of years unexpired, yet he hath been, and still is contented to decline that claime, and submit to such a reasonable Rent for the same as the Committee of the Revenue shall propose; And in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suance hereof, the then Farmors of the Customes have by Order of the said Committee of the Navy (as I am informed) returned a certificate, whereby the true values of the said Customs of Lead may appear; I have therefore thought fit, humbly to recommend the said Certificate, together with the Petition of the Miners of <hi>Derby</hi>-shire and <hi>Devon,</hi> and his Propositions for the publick good; and make it my request that he may speedily Farm the said Customs of Lead, during the time of his former grant, whereby his adventures for discovering Minerals, and recovering the deserted works of this Kingdom, may be incouraged to joyn with him in so common a good, least hee be inforced to leave this Realm, and so good a work perish by his absence: For truly Sir, this last discovery of his in the County of <hi>Devon,</hi> with the report of other his proceedings, hath almost per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded him to become an Adventurer; Who remains,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humble Servant,</hi> Tho. Fairfax.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Queenstreet,</hi>
                  <date>14 <hi>Martii,</hi> 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Miners contemplative Prayer in his solitary Delves, which is conceived requisite to be published, that the Reader may know, his heart implores providence for his Mineral in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, aswel as petitions liberty from men to dig for treasure in their barren Mountains.</head>
            <p>MOst glorious and omniscient Lord God, who inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Eternity, and by thy omnipotent <hi>fiat</hi> didst in the beginning create the admirable fabrick of the Universe; the Heavens are thy Throne, and the Earth is thy Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoole, on which thou didst frame our first Parent of red Clay, and from thence gavest him his name, into whose No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strils thou didst breath the Spirit of Life, enduing him with a reasonable Soule, and madest him Lord of all thy Creatures; But he being in honor could not abide so, but became like the Beast that perisheth, through the treachery of that first Rebel Satan, who ever since endeavoreth to supplant his wretched posterity, of whom my sinful self am
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199121:43"/> one. Give me therefore (O Lord) a true sense of mine own sins without despaire, sincere contrition, unfeigned sorrow and earnest repentance without hypocrisie; make my Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers fervent, holy and grateful, that they may come before thee as the incense of a true penitent soule; for a broken and contrite heart is a sacrifice which thou wilt not despise: And now, O God, having first sought thy mercy on my soule, give me leave to implore thy blessing on my temporal affairs to thy sole glory. O Lord, thy Spirit hath affected mine with the speculation and practice of Mineral Philosophy, and thou wert pleased to bless that most Royal and antient Philosopher, who understood and writ of the natures of all vegetables, from the <hi>Cedar</hi> of <hi>Lebanon</hi> to the pellitory or mosse on the wall, as plainly appeared by the success of his Miners transported by <hi>Hyram's</hi> Mariners to <hi>Opher,</hi> whence they returned with 450 Talents of gold, for effecting whereof that King built and rigged a powerfull Navy at <hi>Ezron Geber</hi> on the red sea, with a vast expence of his own or peoples <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reasure; But (O Lord) my modest designe requires no such charge or means, the propositions of that great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Philosopher, my worthy honored Lord, are to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover those hidden Treasures, which thy inscrutable wisdom hath lodged in the Bowels of the most barren mountaines, and desperately deserted Mineral works of our native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. It is true (Lord) they that descend to the Sea in ships see they wonders in the depth thereof; but such as search the secret Entrails of the Earth, to find out thy concealed won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders there, carry their lives in their hands, being free among the dead, whence they pray unto thee, and praise thy marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous works of nature, when men ride over their heads. But (O Lord) the insatiate thirst of riches or vaine glory spurs not me on to this dangerous and laborious attempt, but my zeale to thy glory, and my Countreys good. <hi>Solomon</hi> beautified thine own Temple which he had built with his far sought Mineral Treasure, and I would therefore willingly erect a house to the honor of his name; in which fabrick (designed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199121:43"/> by my honored Master) true Christian Philosophers, of eminent knowledge, virtuous lives, and holy conversations, might by practical search and discoveries reveale to succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ages these beneficent rarities, and profitable experiments which that great King first treated of, being lost (as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived) to all mankind through thy several Judgements thrown in thine own backsliding people, till that Lord (my quondam Master) assisted by thy Spirit of wisdome, did in his natural History, and that most excellent model in his <hi>New Atlantis</hi> propose to the world a new means to make use of them, to thy glory, and the benefit of all thy servants, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any considerable charge to this or any other State. But (O Lord) the blindness, stupidity and diffidence of mans heart hath as yet obstructed the procedure thereof. <hi>Dives</hi> desired no other means then a messenger from Hell for the conversion of his Brethren which he had misled; now the living which converse with the subterranean spirits cannot be believed in reporting thy wonders in the bosome of the Earth. The <hi>Ninevites</hi> were converted when thy fugitive prophet brought them a penitential Sermon out of the belly of the Whale; grant (O my God) that I which am at present buried alive, and secluded from the World may be thence heard by thee, and so credited by the present ruling Power, that I thy humble suppliant (who like the poore bedridden men at the Poole of <hi>Bethesda</hi> have lain long impotent and unable to move) may find some faithful Patriots to assist my cause, and make them sensible that I beg nothing but that which is lost, and the help of the dead onely to recover it. The Mines that I petition for are drowned, and their works desperately deserted; the persons I propose for their reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, are such as are dead in Law, and crave as a mercy to be buried in them, by a patient undergoing their punishment as pioneers, and turning their necessities into such vertuous actions, rather then a forc'd banishment should expose them to a seven years slavery in forreign plantations. Diamonds, best cut Diamonds, the stony-hearted are fittest to cut the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199121:44"/> stony Addits of the Mines, and like to like will agree best, when a penitential Soule strikes the blow. For (O Lord) we all know, the Prodigal Child was punisht with its oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site; and believe all others have congruity in the like, when thy only Son was forc'd for taking upon him the sins of man, to descend himself into Hell before he could ascend into Heaven; and who knows (O Lord) but that this Mineral imployment is the best way found out for us Mortals, to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline all offenders capable of mercy, with discovering thy concealed treasures, and make such thy onely creatures, when the person which thou placest over them by thy Ministers of State, shall take delightfull care in their education and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, to thy own glory and the publick good, since thou joyest more in one of them then in 99 righteous, that need no repentance. O Lord, in these designs I earnestly beg thy assistance, since thy Son our Saviour hath bid us to ask, seek and knock, that wee may obtain, find and be admitted; pardon then my confidence, diligence and importunity: I have now spent many Lustres of my Life, and some treasure in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution of this design; O let me effect it so to thy glory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I goe hence, as my Feoffees in trust may not be discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to go on where I have left; for time makes haste, to call for natures debt, and Death is none of thy Creature. Let not then my worst Creditor be onely satisfied, before thou hast assisted me in some measure to pay the Debt of Zeale and Obedience which I owe to thee, that of Love and Service due to my native County, the reall sums due to confiding friends, and the great Debt of gratitude to the memory of my famous Master, Foster-Father and Instructor in these undertakings. Pardon then my sins, and grant this my Boone, since mercy and bounty are the most essential Attributes of thy Glory; to whom all Honor, Obedience, Praise and Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving is now and ever due. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="engraving">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:199121:44"/>
            <head>The Impressa of <hi>Mr. Bushell's</hi> golden Medall.
<figure>
                  <p>·FRA· BACON· VICECO· S<seg rend="sup">CT.</seg> ALBAN· ANGLIAE· CANCELL·</p>
                  <p>EST· QVI· CLAVSA· RECLVDIT· THO· BVSHELL· DEVS·</p>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>THe Lord <hi>St. Alban's Atlantis</hi> is a Magazine of compendious (but sublime) documents to enrich a Common-wealth with universal Notions, as far above a vulgar capacity, as the Emperial Heavens are the Earth; for which cause himself stiled it his <hi>Solomons</hi> house, or six daies work: But the way to advance a proportionable Revenue (proposed by his Philosophicall Theory) to accomplish the vast design of such a magnificent structure, without a Princes Purse, will seeme as abstruse to some acute apprehensions, as the immortal descent of the Soule to animate the Embryon in the Wombe: yet if any responsible Persons are incredulous of Mr. <hi>Bushell's</hi> proceedings to perfect the said Lords Philosophical Theory in Mineral discoveries, according to his undertakings, let them, or any other that have heretofore given him credit upon the late Kings score, or his own, repaire to the assurance Office at the Royall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, where they shall have tendred (by Friends of his) Medals of Gold, by way of Mart, according to the Tenor of the ensuing Bill, so soon as it is setled in Parliament for their encouragement, and himself hath liberty to attend providence in the success.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="receipt">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199121:45"/>
            <p>KNow all men by these presents, That I <gap reason="blank" extent="2 words">
                  <desc> _____ _____ </desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> in the County of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> do hereby acknowledge to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Trustees for the late Lord <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor Bacon's</hi> Mineral design, that is now to be practised by his menial Servant. <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> Esq; one Medall of Gold (with that Lords Effigies) of the full value of <hi>5 <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> by way of Mart, upon condition to pay unto the abovesaid <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> their Executors, Administrators, or Assigns, the several summs of money following, that is to say, the summ of <hi>5 <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> for every one pound of the said Medall, If the said <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> shall within <hi>18</hi> moneths from the date hereof, by himself, his Agents, and Assignes, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance out of his Mineral undertakings in recovering the drowned works of <hi>Rowpits</hi> upon the Forrest of <hi>Mendyp,</hi> and other deserted places within the Territories of this Commonwealth, the sum or value of <hi>500 <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> per week in <hi>Copper, Tinn,</hi> or <hi>Lead</hi> mixed with <hi>Silver,</hi> or in all for the whole yeare following, by the approbation of the Mineral grand Jury of <hi>Chewton,</hi> and the Warden of the Mint of the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London</hi> for the time being upon their Oaths; and upon like condition to pay unto the said <gap reason="blank" extent="2 words">
                  <desc> _____ _____ </desc>
               </gap> their Executors, &amp;c. the summ of <hi>10 <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> more, for every one pound of the said Medall, if the said <hi>Tho. Bushell</hi> shall within <hi>18</hi> moneths more from the date hereof by himself, his Agents and Workmen, advance out of the Minerall works as aforesaid, <hi>1000 <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> per week for the whole yeare following: And for the payment of all and every the said sums of money, so to be well and truly paid, I the said <gap reason="blank" extent="2 words">
                  <desc> _____ _____ </desc>
               </gap> doe bind me, my Heirs, Executors, and Administrators firmly by these presents, In witness whereof I the said <gap reason="blank" extent="2 words">
                  <desc> _____ _____ </desc>
               </gap> doe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto put my hand and seale this <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199121:45"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>